<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dissertation concerning the antiquity of temples wherein is shewn, that there were none before the tabernacle, erected by Moses in the wilderness from histories, sacred and profane.</title>
            <author>Hill, Joseph, 1625-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43789</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1998</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19706</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12442893</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12442893</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62134</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43789)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62134)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 942:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dissertation concerning the antiquity of temples wherein is shewn, that there were none before the tabernacle, erected by Moses in the wilderness from histories, sacred and profane.</title>
                  <author>Hill, Joseph, 1625-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 50, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Joseph Hill. cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>At head of title: I.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8]</note>
                  <note>Index: p. [8]</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church history.</term>
               <term>Temples.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62134:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62134:1"/>
            <p>I DISSERTATION CONCERNING THE ANTIQUITY OF TEMPLES.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſhewn, That there were none before the TABERNACLE, Erected by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the WILDERNESS: FROM HISTORIES, Sacred and Profane.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the Bible and Three Crowns in <hi>Cheapſide.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:62134:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62134:2"/>
            <p>HONORATISSIMO Do. Do. GULIELMO TRUMBUL,</p>
            <p>Equiti aurato.</p>
            <p>Non minus virtutibus, quam titulis ornato.</p>
            <p>Apud Regem Galliarum, necnon Imp, Turcicum, Olim Legato.</p>
            <p>Nuper Quaeſtorum aerarij Socio: Nune Gulielmo M. Brit. Regi Ab Epiſtolis, &amp; Sanctioribus conſilijs.</p>
            <p>Itemque In conventu Ordinum Regni, Senatori integerrimo.</p>
            <p>Hanc qualem qualem Diſſertationem, Quam humillimè, <abbr>D. D. C. L. Mq</abbr> JOSEPHUS HILL.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:62134:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62134:3"/>
            <head>READER.</head>
            <p>HAving a deſign to publiſh a few Diſſertations, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome Opinions, that have in the late Times been ventilated amongst us; I ſhall briefly ſhew to what Subjects they have relation: A long Preface being no ways congruous to a ſhort Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>This Firſt is meerly Hiſtorical, referring to the Times of the Old Teſtament concerning <hi>the Antiquity of Temples.</hi> Of which Subject, many Authors have ſpoken by the by; but ſcarce any induſtriouſly and fully. <hi>Hoſpinian</hi> indeed hath ſaid ſomething thereof; but ſo little, and ſuperficially, in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of his copious handling other matters, that 'tis next to nothing for ſatisfaction therein. And none in our own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, that I have ſeen at leaſt, hath treated of this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. There is one <hi>R. T.</hi> that publiſhed a ſmall Tract in <hi>12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. A. D. 1638. de Templis;</hi> wherein he diſcourſes of the ancient Manner of building, conſecrating, and adorning of Churches, according to the Mode of thoſe times, but nothing of their Antiquity. Concerning which, I have from ſacred and prophane Hiſtories, ſaid what I think ſufficient for this preliminary Diſſertation.</p>
            <p>The Second hath reference to the Times of the Goſpel, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Artificial Churches;</hi> wherein the common Opinion of Proteſtants is defended. That the Primitive Chriſtians nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther built, nor had any publick ſeparate Places, appropriate for the publick Worſhip of God, for above Two hundred Years after our Bleſſed Saviours Aſcenſion; but only ſuch private Places of reſort, as were moſt convenient, and ſecure
<pb facs="tcp:62134:4"/>in thoſe Times of Perſecution. Which is alſo the Opinion of the Ancient Fathers, and Hiſtorians generally, as ſhall in due place be manifeſted. In after Ages, when Superſtition and Popery prevailed, ſeveral Authors, the better to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Holineſs of Churches, began to aſſert, That from the beginning Chriſtians had publick Places, dedicated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to their worſhipping God; although, both then and ever ſince, all of this Opinion acknowledg thoſe Edifices were nothing ſo large, or ſtately, as the Temples of the Heathens, or the Churches of Chriſtians, in and after <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s time, when Chriſtianity was generally embraced. But I hope to make it apparent, that this <hi>Salvo</hi> will not ſerve their tarn, nor all the Arguments that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Baronius</hi> have brought; which ſome Learned Proteſtants of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have made uſe of, more eſpecially <hi>Fuller</hi> in's Miſcella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and <hi>Mode</hi> after him, (though he mentions him not) who hath a large Diſcourſe on this Subject, yet not ſufficient to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their Opinion.</p>
            <p>A Third Diſſertation concerus the Holineſs of Churches. Which not only the Papiſts, but many good Proteſtants alſo contend for. Although our Saviour hath taken away all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Places under the Goſpel; as Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> in his <hi>Diſſwaſive from Popery,</hi> c. 4. hath ſufficiently proved. The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or chief ground of their Miſtake is, in reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling our Churches, to the Temple, which have only Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Jewiſh Synagogues, as many Learned Men have ſhewn. For there was but one Temple for all the <hi>12</hi> Tribes, and none entred into it but the Prieſts, and the High. Prieſt once a Tear into the Holy of Holies, on the day of Expiation; the People aſſembling only in the outward Courts: Whereas the Synagogues were for all the People's meeting therein, for the Moral Worſhip of God, on ſuch times as he had ordained. And as God's ſpecial Manifeſtation of himſelf, in any place, intitles it to a relative Holineſs for the time, <hi>Exod. 3.5. Joſh. 5.15. Acts. 7.33.</hi> and <hi>2 Peter I. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 18.</hi> ſo by his
<pb facs="tcp:62134:4"/>more eſpecial Reſidence in the Tabernacle and Temple, they became holy, <hi>Exod. 40.9, 10, 11.</hi> and being typical of our bleſſed Saviour, hallowed the Service of his People, as he tells us, <hi>Matth. 23.17, 19, 20, 21.</hi> But where read we of God's dwelling in the Synagogues, or Chriſtian Churches, more than in other places where he is wor ſhipped? only of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Preſence with his own Ordinances which hallow the Place for the time, not the Place them. For even the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Sacraments, conſecrated by Chriſt's Appointment, have no other relative Holineſs, but in their Sacramental uſe. And the Church of <hi>England</hi> in ſome caſes, admits their Adminiſtration in private Houſes, making no doubt of God's Acceptance thereof there, as well as in the publick Churches.</p>
            <p>The laſt Task will be touching <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Altars:</hi> Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that theſe properly belong only to the Jewiſh, and not otherwiſe than improperly to the Chriſtian Religion; the former being never uſed otherwiſe in the New Teſtament, and the latter only once for our Saviour. And that moſt of the Allegations from Antiquity for their uſe, are either from ſuppoſititious Authors, or ſuch as fall ſhort of proving, that for which they are alledged.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:62134:5"/>
            <head>INDEX.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>OF Temples in general,</hi> Page 1-4.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Their Antiquity from the Old Teſtament,</hi> p. 5. §. 1-7.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>And from prophane Hiſtory,</hi> §. 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Their Original, amongst</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Ethiopians, §. 8.</item>
                     <item>Grecians, §. 9.</item>
                     <item>Italians, §. 10.</item>
                     <item>Pelaſgians, <hi>and other</hi> Grecians, §. 11, 12, 13.</item>
                     <item>Egyptians, §. 14, 15, 16.</item>
                     <item>Oſiris <hi>and</hi> Iſis, §. 17, 18, 19.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>The</hi> Aſſyrians <hi>and</hi> Babylonians, §. 20.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Concluſion,</hi> p. 46.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 11. line 32. for <hi>horum</hi> read <hi>harum.</hi> P. 17. l. 20. for <hi>and</hi> read <hi>of. Ibid.</hi> l. 24. r. 2514. P. 18. l. 33. r. <hi>Tatianus.</hi> P. 21. l. 26. r. <hi>ademtis.</hi> P. 24. l. 23. r. <hi>Arcades. Ibid.</hi> l. 33. r. <hi>Lycaons.</hi> P. 32. l. 34. <hi>Lindus.</hi> P. 39. l. 34. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.12.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62134:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>DISSERTATION I.</hi> Of the Antiquity of Temples; and whether there were any before the Sanctuary.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>IT is requiſite to ſpeak ſomething of Temples in general, before we proceed to treat of their Antiquity. It is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to inſiſt on the Etymology of the word, or the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonima's thereof, their general Parts or Utenſils; which may be ſeen in many Philologers, and even in Engliſh in the large Hiſtorical Dictionary newly publiſhed. It is enough to my purpoſe, that they were Places built for Publick Worſhip. Concerning which, the Learned Antiquary <hi>Lilius Giraldus</hi> (whoſe Works are lately printed at <hi>Leyden</hi>) in his Hiſtory of the Gods, <hi>Syntagm.</hi> 17 faith, <hi>Zenonis dogma fuit Templa Deorum non aedaficanda.</hi> It was <hi>Zeno</hi>'s opinion, that Temples ought not to be built unto the Gods. And diſlikes that of <hi>Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus,</hi> in his Admonition to the Gentiles, <hi>Superſtitio Templa condere perſuaſit. Quae cnim prius bominum Sepulchra fuerunt, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificentius condita, Templorum appellatione vocata ſunt.</hi> Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on perſuaded to build Temples. For thoſe Structures, which were before Sepulchres, being after magnificently built, were called Temples. But approves the Abbot of <hi>Cluny</hi>'s opinion, who writing againſt the <hi>Petrobuſions</hi> (whom <hi>Morney</hi> accounts good Chriſtians, even the ſame with the <hi>Woldenſians</hi>) imputes it is an errour in them <hi>quod dicunt, Baſilicas vel Altaria fieri non debere,</hi> &amp;c. to affirm that Temples and Altars ſhould not be made. But the Maſs being the chief uſe of their Temples in thoſe times (as <hi>Bellarm. de cultu Sanct. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4.) in this regard they might well be oppoſed; for that they denied the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Edifices, for the ſolemn Worſhip of God, is no way credible. The firſt Founder of Temples <hi>Clem. Alexandr.</hi> in's Admonition to the Gentiles, <hi>p.</hi> 28. Gr. <hi>Lat.</hi> conceives to have been <hi>Phoroneus,</hi> or <hi>Merops.</hi> And ſo alſo <hi>Arnobius l.</hi> 6. <hi>Varro</hi> in's
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62134:6"/>
                  <hi>Admiranda, Aeacus</hi> the Son of <hi>Jupiter.</hi> And <hi>Lactantius, Divin. Inſtit. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 10. faith the firſt Temple was erected in the days of <hi>Jupiter. Joh. Leo Baptista,</hi> in's Book of Architecture, thinks <hi>Janus</hi>'s Temple the firſt. But the ſame <hi>Clemens Strom l.</hi> 5. wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>Moſes,</hi> faith, He ſuffered not Altars and Temples to be erected in many places, having built one Temple (he means the Sanctuary) did hereby declare unto all, that there was but one World and one God; alledging <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 66.1. and <hi>Acts</hi> 17.48. and commending <hi>Zeno</hi> for ſaying, in's Book of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, <hi>non oportere Templa faccre, nec ſimulacra,</hi> that Temples and Images ought not to be made. For a Temple is not of any great price, nor an holy thing, being it is the Work of Artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers. And in his Seventh Book diſtinguiſheth of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly rendred a Temple, which he takes for that which is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy; and this he ſaith is twofold; God himſelf, and that which is built in honour of him; and this with him is the Church; which he calls the Church of God, not made with hands, but made the Temple of God, by the will of God. <hi>Non enim nunc locum, ſed electorum congregationem appello Eccleſiam.</hi> For I do not now call the place, but the Congregation of God's choſen ones the Church. <hi>Origen</hi> alſo againſt <hi>Celſus l.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 390, 391. profeſſeth, Chriſtians beware of building liveleſs and dead Temples to the giver of all Life. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. which he ſpeaks to depreciate thoſe Works of men, that men might not think God is honoured by ſuch things, which for the matter of them are common, and for the figure and ſhape, the works of mens hands. As alſo to refute the Heathens, who thought God was more honoured, and better ſerved in ſuch Temples, than in the poor Conventicles, and Oratories of Chriſtians; and was in a more eſpecial manner preſent in ſuch Temples, then in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places. For we know that now under the Goſpel, God hath determined his Worſhip to no place, any more than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Flood, or the days of the Patriarchs before <hi>Moſes.</hi> Who by God's appointment made the Sanctuary, which yet was not confined to any place; but portable, and moveable to and fro for 400 years; till the Temple was built, in a place appointed by God, to which all Sacrifices acceptable, were to be brought, and there offered upon his Altar. And this was done, as <hi>Athanaſius Epist. ad Adelph. contra Arrianos,</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64. for a figure of Chriſt's Body which was to come; and when that Truth ſignified, began evidently to be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62134:6"/>preached, the Shadow was deſtroyed. So <hi>Arnobius l.</hi> 6. ſaith, We muſt not think, that God is delighted in Temples, becauſe built of Marble, and gloriouſly ſet forth with Gold: to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the opinion of the Heathens, who profeſſed, that if their Gods were prayed unto, <hi>ſub axe nudo, &amp; ſub aethereo regimine, nihil audiunt,</hi> under the cope of Heaven, and in the open Air, they would not hear. And <hi>Lactantius, Div. Inst. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 25. <hi>Non Templa illi congeſtis in altitudinem ſaxis extruenda ſunt, in ſuo cuique conſecrandus est pectore:</hi> Temples are not to be built unto him of Stones laid one upon another to a great height, every one ought to conſecrate him in his own heart. Not that theſe Ancients thought it unlawful, for Chriſtians to have Temples: but in oppoſition to the Heathens opinion, That God accepted of no Worſhip, but that performed in Temples made with hands; and that the more coſtly they were, the better he was pleaſed: as <hi>Lactant. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>Nec ullam religionem putant, ubi illa non fulſerint:</hi> They think there's no Religion where theſe are not ſhining; <hi>i. e.</hi> with Gold, precious Stones, Ivory, <hi>&amp;c. Itaque ſub obten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Deorum avaritia &amp; cupiditas colitur, credunt cnim Deos amare, quicquid ipſi concupiſcunt.</hi> Under colour of Divine Worſhip, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs is worſhipped. For they think the Gods love, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they are in love withal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> in like manner, in's Evangelical Preparation <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9. ſhews, That men in moſt ancient times, took no care or pains about building Temples. And that the firſt builders of them, were Heathens, with the occaſion thereof. And in very truth, we have not the leaſt colour of Evidence, for any built before the Flood: tho' we read how God was ſerved from the firſt by Sacrifice, in the ſtory of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel;</hi> and was worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, no doubt, by the holy Patriarchs. For tho' a degenerate condition increaſed, amongſt the Poſterity of <hi>Cain;</hi> yet <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> after the promiſe of Grace, continued in the ſame gracious courſe, with others of their Off ſpring, who followed their Inſtitution and Religion, eſpecially in the race of <hi>Seth.</hi> And in his days, eſpecially about the birth of his Son <hi>Enoch;</hi> for the Scripture teſtifies that, <hi>then men began to call upon the name of the Lord.</hi> And near unto the Flood, we read of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, between the Sons of God, and the Daughters of Men: tho' afterwards this came to be exceedingly confound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which ended in a natural Confuſion of them all, through God's juſt judgment. After the Flood 400 years, <hi>Abram</hi> by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62134:7"/>Divine admonition left his own Country, and came into <hi>Canan;</hi> where he and his Poſterity liv'd long in Tents, like Strangers; and erected Altars, where God appeared to them, and worſhipped him in the open Air. And <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 13. the ſame <hi>Euſebius</hi> faith, That it becomes wiſe men, with open face to preach unto all, <hi>that they do not reverence thoſe things which are ſeen with bodily eyes: but him alone whom no man ſeeth, even the Architect and Maker of all,</hi> with much more to that purpoſe, and that <hi>we ſhould not think, to worſhip the Divine Power, with build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Temples.</hi> And accordingly, in his firſt Book of Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Demonſtration, <hi>p.</hi> 18. <hi>Graeco. Lat.</hi> To them who thought that God ought to be worſhipped only at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> or on certain Hills, and in definite places, our Saviour for good cauſe anſwered, <hi>The hour cometh, and now is,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 4.23, 24. And adds, that now in theſe times of Grace, we are brought to the ſame manner of Worſhip, which was among the Patriarchs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Moſes,</hi> which he calls <hi>eadem benedictio,</hi> like that of <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. And <hi>p.</hi> 23. introduceth the Lord Chriſt ſpeaking. The Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded men to go out of all other places, to a certain definite place of the World, there to worſhip God: But I command you, not to ſeek God out in any certain cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the World, nor in Hills, nor in Temples made with hands: but giving all men liberty from ſuch reſtraint, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand every one to worſhip, and adore God, at his own houſe and home. Not that he held it unlawful to worſhip God in material Temples; but only to ſhew, that now there is no ſuch neceſſity, as ties men to the Service of God in Temples, as if he were better ſerved there than in other places. Like as <hi>Auſtin Tom.</hi> 6. <hi>contra Serm. Arrian. cui Templum non facimus, ſed nos ipſi ſumus;</hi> not as if no Temples were made by them, or ought to be; but in effect, That we not only make a Temple, but are his Temples. As <hi>Xixtus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> and Martyr ſaid, <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum ſanctum eſt Deo mens pura,</hi> a pure Mind is a Temple holy unto God: This ſanctifies all places, and the Prayers ſent up unto him in ſuch a Temple, is always accepted of him. And how little Conſecrated places were inſiſted on, in <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s time, when Chriſtianity was ſet up and countenanced by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, may be ſeen in <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s. Apology for his preaching in ſuch at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> as was neither finiſhed nor conſecrated; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging <hi>Alexander</hi> his Predeceſſor for doing the like; and others at <hi>Tryers</hi> and <hi>Aquilea.</hi> We ſhall now proceed to enquire further into</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62134:7"/>
               <head>The Antiquity of <hi>Temples.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Whether there were any before the Sanctuary made by <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE read in the Old Teſtament, of Altars very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arly and frequently, without any Temples. Implyed in <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi>'s Offerings unto the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. expreſt, of <hi>Noah</hi>'s building an Altar unto the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.20. ſo <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 26.25. and <hi>Jacob</hi> at <hi>Bethel, Gen.</hi> 35.7. <hi>Elias</hi> likewiſe in his Contention with the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.32. And in the New Teſtament, of the Heathens Altar at <hi>Athens, Acts</hi> 17.23. (the Story whereof is related by <hi>Diog. Laertius</hi> in the Life of <hi>Epimenides,</hi> and <hi>L. Vives</hi> on <hi>Auſtin de C. D. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 17. and others) And <hi>Walafridus Strabo</hi> Writes, That at firſt both the Worſhippers of God, and of the Devil, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed their Service in the open Air; but when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to make Idols, then, and not till then, and upon that oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, they began to build Temples. I ſhall not trouble the Reader with a multitude of Authours, that have written of the Original and Progreſs of Idolatry. I think <hi>Mercerus</hi> judgeth right, that there was none before the Flood: And though ſome Rabbins I know, and alſo <hi>Tertullian</hi> thought, there were Idols and Idolatry in the old World; yet <hi>Cyril l.</hi> 3. againſt <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in's <hi>Panarium,</hi> with many others, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. And that the Sin of thoſe days, which provoked God to drown the World, was Irreligiouſneſs and Prophaneneſs, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Superſtition and Idolatry. For the cauſe of the Flood is mentioned in general, that all Fleſh had corrupted their ways. It was very general, and therefore the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to corrupt the Earth. In <hi>Enoch</hi>'s days, it ſeems by his Propheſie mentioned by <hi>Jude,</hi> that prophane Perſons did ſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſpeak, and practiſe againſt God's Servants; with which reproachful carriage, carnal Men being overcome, became pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane alſo; and the good being taken away by death, there was a general defection. In ſpecial we read, that <hi>the earth was full of violence;</hi> and this increaſed upon the degenerate condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God's People. <hi>For the ſons of God ſaw the daughters of Men that they were fair, and they took them Wives of all that they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62134:8"/>liked,</hi> Gen. 6.2. which provoked the Lord in an high degree, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>And hereupon there were Children born unto them, which were mighty men, and men of r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Then Carnal Security was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great, as our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignifieth <hi>Luke</hi> 17.26, 27. which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> contempt of God's Word; and alſo of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and long ſuffering in his Works. For he bare with them an 120 years, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Noah</hi> a Preacher of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs unto them; thus the Goodneſs of God led them to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance both ways, but they were diſobedient, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. and thereby treaſured up wrath againſt the day of wrath, and the Flood came and ſwept them all away, ſave eight Perſons. In all this we have no Evidence of any Sin of Idolatry committed by them; and had that been their ſin, it is unlikely the Holy Ghoſt would have pretermitted the mention thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. After this the experience of God's wrath breaking forth into ſo ſore a Judgment, and cauſing ſo great a Devaſtation, as to lay a whole World waſt; this I ſay might juſtly work in them the fear of God, and make them generally become the more devout, while the remembrance of ſo general a Deluge remained; and this might well be continued for ſo many years as they ſurvived who had ſeen the Flood. Now we read that <hi>Noah</hi> lived 350 years after the Flood, and <hi>Sem</hi> his Son 498 years. How long <hi>Ham</hi> and <hi>Japhet</hi> ſurvived after the Flood is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. This Devotion proceeding only from a natural cauſe, as in all Perſons unregenerate, could prove but natural, and therefore the more apt to be corrupted with Idolatry: as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it was very timely, even in the days of <hi>Terah Abraham</hi>'s Father, as we read <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24. though <hi>Noah</hi> himſelf, the Father of them all, ſurvived a 128 years in the very days of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah; Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithful being born but the third year after <hi>Noah</hi>'s death; <hi>Sem</hi> yet living 152 years after this, as who died but ten years before <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> the twin Sons of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Rebeckah</hi> were born. This <hi>Jacob</hi> with all his Children went down into <hi>Egypt,</hi> whither <hi>Joſeph</hi> was gone many years before, and in all the Sacred Hiſtory con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s dwelling there, and the Egyptians vexing and oppreſſing of them, until the Lord's wonderful Deliverance of them, though we read of the Gods of <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Numb.</hi> 33.4. as alſo how the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were corrupted with their <hi>Idols, Ezech.</hi> 20.7. yet we read of no Temples they had. And <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> though he would
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62134:8"/>have had them Sacrifice to their God, in the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet he knew full well they had no Temple for this; and when he promiſed to give them leave to go into the Wilderneſs to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice there, provided they went not far, he knew there was no Temple for them. But the third month after their coming out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> at Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> the Lord took order for the building of a Sanctuary, ſaying unto <hi>Moſes, Let them make me a Sanctuary that I may dwell among them,</hi> Exod. 25.8, 9. And I am apt to be perſwaded, that hereupon the Devil wrought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Gentiles his Vaſſals, to build Sanctuaries and Temples for their Idols, as places for their habitation and dwelling among them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For the Devil is commonly ſaid to be God's Ape, he doth affect to imitate God. Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> hath obſerved this in ſetting down his opinion concerning the firſt plantation of <hi>America,</hi> which he conceives to have been wrought originally by the Devil, by his perſuaſions drawing a Colony thither out of theſe Northern Parts, and that long ſince the preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel began, yea, not very many hundred years ago: The <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> not finding by any means of Tradition from the Father to the Son, that they had been planted there above 400 years before their coming amongſt them, as the <hi>Mexican</hi> Hiſtory doth teſtifie. And like as when Idolatry at the firſt began to ſpread, and to corrupt the Family of <hi>Terah Abraham</hi>'s Father, the Lord called him away from thence into another Country, who followed him, not knowing whither he went: So the Devil, when he ſaw what a ſtrange alteration was made in the World, by the preaching of the Goſpel, and fearing leſt he ſhould be turned out of all; he projected a courſe of drawing ſome of his Diſciples into a new World out of all danger, from the ſound of the Goſpel, that ſo he might rule the more ſafely over them without all controul; as indeed he did, and that in ſuch ſort as never in the like manner before, ſince the time that Mankind firſt fell into his clutches.</p>
               <p>In all Ages, ever ſince his Fall, his practiſe hath been to draw Man from his Maker. <hi>Cupiunt perditi perdere</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>) <hi>&amp; depravati errorem pravitatis infundere, &amp; cum ſint ipſi pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nales, quaerunt ſibi ad paenam comites.</hi> And accordingly as he finds them, by one way or other, moſt apt to be led away from God; ſo his practiſe is to work upon them agreeably to their Natures. If he finds them profanely diſpoſed, his courſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62134:9"/>is to confirm them therein, until he hath brought them to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Atheiſm, if God permit him ſo far to prevail: but in caſe he find them awed with fear of a Divine Providence; then he laboureth to work them to the ſervice of himſelf; wherein he plays the part of a Thief as well as of an Ape, labouring by all means to rob God of his Glory, as the Apoſtle ſheweth in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20. where he faith, <hi>Know ye not that the things which the Gentiles ſacrifice, they ſacrifice to Devils and not to God.</hi> For whether he draws them to worſhip the Sun, Moon and Stars, and all the Hoſt of Heaven; or their deceaſed Anceſtors, he draws them from God the Creator, unto the Creature; or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pretence of theſe, to worſhip the Evil Spirits themſelves, eſpecially when by giving forth his Oracles in ſuch places, where the Images of their Anceſtors were worſhipped, he had ſo infatuated them, as to think that ſuch Places were inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God himſelf; and thus the Oracles there given forth with great ſubtilty and colluſion, were received as Divine. Thus hath the World beén drawn from God, and the Worſhip which is due to him, beſtowed upon the Devil his profeſt Enemy, and as oppoſite unto him as Darkneſs is to Light.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Now as for Inward and Spiritual Worſhip moſt proper to the Nature of God, theſe Angels of Darkneſs know full well wherein it conſiſts; as which was ſometimes performed by themſelves, even then, when God laid the Foundation of the Earth, and the Angels were newly created as God's firſt Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip. For even then we read, <hi>Job</hi> 38.7. <hi>The morning ſtars ſang together, and all the ſons of God ſhouted for joy.</hi> And this Worſhip by Prayer, Praiſe and Obedience due to God, he pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſeth to draw to himſelf: that Man made after the Image of God, may conform himſelf to the will of the Devil. But as for Outward and Corporal Worſhip, herein the Devil is to ſeek. For to preſcribe that, is meerly at the pleaſure of God, and according to his Wiſdom, which is unknown to the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. As namely, the worſhipping of God by Carnal Sacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, according to all the Variety thereof, as by offering Incenſe and ſweet Odours; Meat-offerings and Drink-offerings; Burnt-offerings of certain kinds of Creatures, Sin-offerings, and Treſpaſs-offerings; and laſtly Peace-offerings, according to all the ſeveral kinds of them. No Angels reaſon, whether of Darkneſs or of Light, is able by convincing Evidence to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that any ſuch Service is a thing pleaſing and acceptable
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62134:9"/>unto God in it ſelf; and unleſs God himſelf ſhall think ſit to preſcribe it congruous in reference to ſuch ends as ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by him. Rather Natural Reaſon is againſt it, God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf being a Spirit, and therefore Spiritual Worſhip, and a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Service ſtands in beſt congruity to his Divine and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Nature: otherwiſe he could not be worſhipped by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which are meer Spirits without any Bodies. The like may be ſaid as concerning a Temple, where all ſuch Rites and Sacrifices are to be performed; for albeit the Actions of Men cannot be performed, but in time and place, yet this is to be underſtood of time and place natural. And indeed there is no time but natural; but place is not only natural but artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial; as Houſes built to dwell in, and the uſe hereof, came not into the World, but by the Sin of Man, whereupon his Body grew expoſed to the Injuries of Wind and Weather, whereto Angels are not: which is one end alſo of the uſe of Garments to cloth us. And we know well, that albeit Sacrifices had their courſe by God's Ordinance (as it ſeems) immediately af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Fall of Man, and that Promiſe made concerning the <hi>Seed of the Woman,</hi> namely, that it ſhould <hi>break the Serpent's head:</hi> yet theſe Sacrifices continued to be offered for ſome thouſands of years on Altars, without any Temples erected for this, as appears by the Sacrifices of the Patriarchs. And after their building, how different were they in their Figure, ſome round, others long, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as alſo in their ſite, the Gentile Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters worſhipping the Sun, had them towards the Eaſt; the <hi>Romans</hi> at firſt towards the Weſt, which they changed before <hi>Auguſtus</hi>'s time to the Eaſt, as <hi>Vitruvius l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5. How much more the ordering of Temples according to the parts thereof, and Utenſils and Furniture, and Ornaments of all thoſe parts, no wit (I think) of Man or Angel, can conclude that any ſuch thing becomes God to dwell in, or there to hear Prayers, and accept the Service performed to him, more than in other places. Unleſs himſelf ſhall be pleaſed, to confine himſelf for ſuch purpoſes, to one place rather than another; which in Scripture phraſe is to place his Name there, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.16. or to record his Name, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.24. or make the memorial of his Name, which <hi>Piſcator</hi> underſtands, <hi>de illuſtribus Dei patefactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus,</hi> as God ſhould be pleaſed to manifeſt himſelf, in illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner, in one place more than another. And we know full well, that when ſuch Ceremonies and Place for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62134:10"/>performance of them were appointed by God; they were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in all the parts of them, for myſterious Prefigurations; and therefore are called <hi>ſhadows of good things to come,</hi> Col. 2.17. Heb. 10.1. Yea and ſome of them, tending to the extream con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of Satan, and his Kingdom, yet ſuch as ſhould be brought to paſs by Satan's own Counſel and Practiſes: as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the betraying and crucifying of the Son of God: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord ſaw it ſit that the preaching and practiſing of ſuch Myſteries, which in due time ſhould be revealed, ſhould be carried in the mean time in the Clouds of Types and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, ſo that Satan himſelf ſhould not be able to diſcover the depth of them, until the time came wherein they were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed. And indeed, there is no greater glory of God that manifeſts it ſelf, in the courſe of his Providence, than the glory of his Wiſdom;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.10, 20.</note> and this is moſt ſeen in taking the Wiſe in their craftineſs, and going beyond them throughout, and making their Devices vain, that it may appear, the wiſeſt of them are but fools in compariſon of him, not only amongſt Men, but among the Angels alſo. For the holy Angels are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with a great deſire to peer into theſe Myſteries, and hereby is made known unto them the manifold wiſdom of God;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.12. Eph. 3.10. Rom. 11.33.</note> 
                  <hi>O the depth of the riches, both of the knowledge and wiſdom of God, how unſearchable are his judgments and his ways paſt finding out. For who hath known the mind of the Lord, or who hath been his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Therefore it ſtood Satan upon it to obſerve what courſe the Lord would be pleaſed to take for his outward Service, that ſo he might uſe his beſt endeavour to oppoſe it: either by alienating the minds of men from that kind of Service, or by corrupting it, drawing their hearts from God, and working them to beſtow that Service upon the Creature. An inſtance of the firſt kind, we may obſerve in the Egyptians, in whom he wrought an extream alienation from the Hebrews, for ſuch was their Superſtition that they might not eat with the Hebrews,<note place="margin">Gen. 43.32.</note> for that was an abomination to the Egyptians. Theſe Hebrews were the People of God, ſo called from the Patriarch <hi>Heber,</hi> who was great Grandfather to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s great Grandfather, <hi>Serug.</hi> This <hi>Heber</hi> lived Nineteen years in the days of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who came down into <hi>Egypt.</hi> It ſeems he had a numerous Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and that might make him and his the more known in the World, even to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the Egyptians in <hi>Jacob</hi>'s days:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62134:10"/>For one of his Sons, <hi>Joktan</hi> by name, had Thirteen Sons, as the Scripture doth expreſs. And <hi>Sem,</hi> that holy Patriarch, is peculiarly noted in Scripture to be the Father of the Sons of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> though he were <hi>Heber</hi>'s great Grandfather. And this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had a myſtery in the ſignification of it, as <hi>Moulin</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives. For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> faith he, is as much as Paſſengers.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.11.</note> And ſuch is the condition of God's Children here; they are but Strangers and Pilgrims. It is afterwards ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 46 34. that <hi>every Shepherd was an abomination to the Egyptians</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vid.</hi> Cunaeus de rep. Hebr. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note>. This we muſt underſtand aright, namely of ſuch Shepherds only as the Hebrews were, who did kill and eat Sheep, or kill and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice them. For it is apparent, that the Egyptians themſelves kept Sheep; and therefore when <hi>Joſeph</hi> bought their Cattel of them for Bread-corn, theſe are reckoned up to have been, not their Horſes and their Aſſes only, but their Flocks and Herds alſo. And <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.3. God threatens to lay his hand upon their Sheep to deſtroy them; but the ſacrificing of them, this was it which the Egyptians accounted abomination. And therefore when <hi>Pharaoh called for</hi> Moſes <hi>and for</hi> Aaron, <hi>and ſaid,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 8.25, 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Go ye and ſacrifice to your God in the Land; Moſes</hi> forthwith anſwered and ſaid, <hi>It is not meet ſo to do: For we ſhall ſacrifice the abomination of the Egyptians to the Lord our God. Lo, ſhall we ſacrifice the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Egyptians before their eyes, and will they not ſtone us?</hi> Nor the ſacrificing of them only, but to kill them for Food was an abomination to the Egyptians. And therefore whereas we read <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.6. that <hi>Potiphar left all that he had in</hi> Joſeph'<hi>s hands, ſave the bread which he did eat:</hi> this both <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Schindler</hi> render thus, <hi>ſave the meat that he did eat;</hi> and <hi>Shin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dler</hi> gives the reaſon why he would not have <hi>Joſeph</hi> meddle with that, to wit, becauſe he was <hi>Carnis Eſor,</hi> an Eater of Fleſh, <hi>Quia eo tempore Egyptij non comedebant carnem, nec lac,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Schindler</hi> on the Root <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nec macta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant oves, &amp; borum paſtores, &amp; comeſtores abominabantur:</hi> The Egyptians in thoſe days did not eat Fleſh nor Milk, nor killed Sheep; and the Keepers and Eaters of Sheep were an abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation unto them. And <hi>Euſebius</hi> in the Second Book of his <hi>Evangelical Preparation, p.</hi> 49. <hi>Graeco-Lat.</hi> makes an enumeration of the Creatures which are Sacred amongſt the Egyptians, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which are Sheep; and adds, <hi>That if any man do pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely kill any one of them,</hi> morte damnatur, <hi>he is put to death.</hi> Theſe Superſtitions were very ancient among the Egyptians, even in the days of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and in the days of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> before
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62134:11"/>
                  <hi>Jacob</hi>'s coming down thither, and how long before I know not.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Nevertheleſs, the Devil being not able to expectorate out of the hearts of all men, that Opinion which had taken deep root, namely, That as there was a God, one or more, which governed the World, and who brought ſore Judgments upon them for their ſins, ſo this God or Gods, were to be appeaſed by ſome courſe or other, and no ſuch courſe for this as Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, a courſe whereof was derived from <hi>Noah</hi> to all his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Therefore the Devil had another way to diſhonour God, by drawing them to Sacrifice to Idols, and to Creatures, inſtead of the Creator; yea, and to the Devil himſelf (being deluded by his Oracles) and that in moſt barbarous manner: for at length he brought them to Sacrifice Men, Women and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unto him, and that under great ſhew of Devotion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we read largely in very many Authors, both Ancient and Modern. I will only mention one notable Story in <hi>Panſanias;</hi> How when a Temple became polluted, by the impure courſes of a young Man and Maid, the Devil gave forth by his Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, that this Prophanation was to be expiated by Sacrifice; and no Sacrifice would ſerve the turn but this: Every year a young Man and Maid muſt be ſacrificed to that God, whoſe Temple had thus been defiled. And this barbarous courſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for certain years; only they beſtowed a denomination upon this God of theirs, calling him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the rigid or cruel God.</hi> And accordingly I am of opinion, that like as Satan had never brought any to ſerve him by Sacrifices (the ancient Heathens by Light of Nature, diſcourſing againſt the unreaſonableneſs of ſuch a Service, as we read in <hi>Diodorus Sicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>) if God had not gone before them in this, inſtructing <hi>Adam</hi> and the Patriarchs, even till the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to ſerve him; and <hi>Noah</hi> leaving this courſe by tradition to his Poſterity, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writes to the like purpoſe, <hi>Ep.</hi> 49. <hi>ad Deo gratias. Hoc ſanè praetereundum non eſt, this is not to be omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Had not the Devils, thoſe rebellious Angels, conceived that Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Prieſthood, Sacrifices, and all other things pertaining thereunto were due to one, that one true God, they would never have urged their Worſhippers to ordain any of theſe things to them.</hi> In like ſort the Devil had never brought them to build Temples for this uſe and ſervice, if God had not taken order with his People to build a Sanctuary unto him that he might dwell amongſt them.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62134:11"/>And accordingly, though Heathens had Temples before <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> built that Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> (for this appears both by the high places which King <hi>Solomon</hi> built for his outlandiſh Wives, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.7, 8. and by the Philiſtims, who had an Houſe for <hi>Dagon,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.2. and <hi>Judges</hi> 16.27. and 9.27. we read how the People <hi>went into the Houſe of their God, and did eat and drink and curſed</hi> Abimelech: and <hi>verſ.</hi> 46. <hi>of the houſe of the god Berith,</hi> and <hi>Judg.</hi> 8.33.) yet I do not find ſufficient evidence of any Temples in uſe with any before the Sanctuary was made, and that to this end, that God might <hi>dwell among them,</hi> Exod. 25.8. And as <hi>Schindler</hi> writeth on the root <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that was <hi>aedificium inſtar templi ex lignis confectum atque it a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutum ut diſſolvi in partes ac rurſus compingi, ac quocunque liberet deferri poſſet;</hi> a ſtructure Temple-like made of Timber, in ſuch ſort as it might be taken aſunder, in all the parts thereof; and again compacted together, that ſo it might be removed from place to place, whitherſoever it pleaſed God to have it carried. A notable inſtruction, that <hi>God would be a Sanctuary unto them, and dwell among them in all places whitherſoever they ſhould come,</hi> Ezek. 11.16. And among other Temples of the Gentiles, whereof we read in Hiſtory, one was <hi>portatile,</hi> a portable Temple, and removed from place to place, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Temple borne or drawn by certain Yoke of Oxen, and that in <hi>Phoenicia,</hi> which is the Country of <hi>Paleſtine.</hi> This <hi>Euſebius</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies in the firſt Book of his <hi>Evangelical Preparation,</hi> and <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. And ſuch a Tabernacle the Scriptures often call by ſuch a word, as is uſually rendred by Temple, as 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.9. and 3.3. and 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.17. and in the <hi>Pſalms</hi> of <hi>David</hi>'s enditing it is found very frequently. For we know that in his days, there was no other Temple, than the Tabernacle. For though it was ſometimes in the heart of <hi>David</hi> to build a Houſe to the Name of the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin"> 1 Kings 8.17, 18, 19.2 Sam. 7.2.</note> when as yet the Ark of the Lord remained amongſt the Curtains: yet we know that the Lord anſwered him, He took it well that he was ſo minded (yet he had conſulted with the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi> firſt, about the matter, before he grew to a Reſolution thereupon) <hi>Nevertheleſs thou ſhalt not build me an Houſe, ſaith the Lord; but thy ſon that ſhall come out of thy Loyns, he ſhall build the Houſe to my Name.</hi> So that till <hi>Solomon</hi>'s reign, there was only a Tabernacle for the Ark of God, wherein was the Mercy Seat, and there the Lord is ſaid to have dwelt, and that in a Cloud, <hi>Lev.</hi> 16.2.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62134:12"/>
                  <hi>Between the Cherubims.</hi> Neither have I yet found any evidence to the contrary, either in Scripture or elſewhere. Before the Flood no evidence of any; though <hi>Mercer</hi> obſerves, they had a place of Meeting for the Service of God: as upon <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. where we read of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi>'s Offering, and God's accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the one, and diſregarding of the other, and that (as it ſeems) in a viſible and ſenſible manner: For hereupon <hi>Cain</hi> was provoked againſt <hi>Abel.</hi> Likewiſe upon the birth of <hi>Enoſh,</hi> when it is ſaid, That <hi>men began to call upon the Name of the Lord, Mercer</hi> makes the ſame obſervation. Neither can we promiſe leſs unto our ſelves of <hi>Adam</hi>'s care for the diſciplining, and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting of his Family, and <hi>Seth</hi>'s after him: and the like may be ſaid of all the holy Patriarchs.<note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> This alſo is manifeſt by the diſtinction made between the Sons of God and Daughters of Men, until the degenerate condition came on, and the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Wall was broken down by promiſcuous Marriages. But in all this, not any evidence of Temples ſeparate, and ſet apart for this.</p>
               <p n="7">7. After the Flood, when <hi>Noah</hi> came out of the Ark, there he built an Altar unto the Lord, and offered a Burnt-offering of every clean Fowl and Beaſt: After this, in the Story of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> the Genealogies being diſpatched, and the diſperſion of the People, by the occaſion of Confuſion of Tongues, we have the erecting of the two firſt Monarchies, the Babylonian by <hi>Nimrod,</hi> and after the ſame time the Aſſyrian by <hi>Aſſur,</hi> who built <hi>Niniveh,</hi> ſo called (as it is thought by very probable conjecture) from the name of his Son <hi>Ninus:</hi> For it is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in Scripture, that Places had their names from the names of ſome chief Perſons that dwelt there. Thus <hi>Egypt</hi> is called <hi>Miſraim,</hi> from <hi>Miſraim</hi> the Son of <hi>Ham,</hi> and the Land <hi>Canaan</hi> from <hi>Canaan,</hi> and ſo <hi>Jonia</hi> from <hi>Javan,</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria</hi> from <hi>Aſſur,</hi> After theſe particulars diſpatched in brief, we have the Story of <hi>Abraham</hi> his Peregrination, who built Altars, where the Lord appeared unto him, and ſo did <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> but we find no Monument of any Temple or ſeparate Houſe they had for God's Service;<note place="margin">Gen. 24.63.</note> but we read of <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s going abroad into the Field to pray. Likewiſe when <hi>Abraham</hi> went down into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> we find not the leaſt indication of any ſuch thing there, nor among the Philiſtims, whilſt <hi>Abraham</hi> ſojourned a good while with them, and <hi>Iſaac</hi> after him: No nor among the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naanites, though we read of <hi>Melchiſedek</hi> the Prieſt of the moſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62134:12"/>High God, and good Correſpondency between <hi>Abraham</hi> and him; yet no mention of any Temple or Houſe of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he performed any Religious Duties to that great God, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſor of Heaven and Earth, whoſe Prieſt he was. Indeed if we ſhould credit ſome uncertain Relations of fabulous Writers, we may find Temples much earlier mentioned. <hi>Albertus Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> in the fourth Book of <hi>Narrations</hi> (cited by <hi>Hoſpinian Tr.</hi> of Images) aſcribes the beginning of Idolatry to <hi>Nimrod,</hi> who as he pretends upon the loſs of his firſt-born <hi>Belus,</hi> to aſſwage his grief, cauſed his Image to be made of Gold, which he ſet up in a Temple built by him, and worſhipped it, and oſſered Sacrifices unto it. <hi>Aventinus</hi> writes, that <hi>Ninus</hi> the Son of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Jupiter</hi> (the ſecond King of the Babylonians the Son of <hi>Nimrod</hi>) cauſed his Fathers image to be made in the midſt of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and a Temple alſo, and Divine Honours to be done unto his Father. Both which are fabulous, and all of this kind, in <hi>Pliny</hi> and <hi>Victor Maſſilienſis.</hi> As alſo in the Apocryphal <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſus,</hi> that <hi>Ninus</hi> adorned <hi>Nineveh,</hi> and was the firſt who built a Temple, and erected Statues to his Father <hi>Belus,</hi> and his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Juno,</hi> and his Grandmother <hi>Rhea.</hi> For we have no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of thoſe early times, but from Scripture, which acquaints us, that <hi>Nimrod</hi> was the Son of <hi>Guſh,</hi> and Grandchild of <hi>Ham,</hi> and Founder of the Babylonian Monarchy: as <hi>Aſhur</hi> was the Son of bleſſed <hi>Shem,</hi> and built <hi>Nineveh,</hi> the Metropolis of the Aſſyrian Monarchy. Which though conſiderably later, yet ſoon overtopt the Babylonian, and continued its Primacy for the greateſt part of many Ages, and in the time of <hi>Eſarchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> after <hi>Babylon</hi> had revolted, reduced it again, and carried <hi>Manaſſes</hi> thither, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33.11. Though ſhortly after, about ten or eleven years, <hi>Nabopollaſar</hi> (or <hi>Nebuchadonaſor</hi>) having taken <hi>Nineveh,</hi> and aſſuming his Son <hi>Nebuchadneſſar</hi> to reign with him, the Babylonian Monarchy ſtarted up again, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertopt the Aſſyrian, through the effeminateneſs of their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as is plain in Hiſtory, and the manner thereof in <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s <hi>Politicks:</hi> which Revolution, was the immediate cauſe under God, of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> Reſtoration. But leaving theſe Relations mentioned by the by,<note place="margin">Gen. 47.28.</note> let's proceed in the infallible Hiſtory of Truth. From the time of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s going down into <hi>Egypt</hi> at Seventeen years of Age, to the time of his firſt ſtanding before <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the year before the Seven plentiful years began, at what time he is ſaid to be Thirty years old, and after <hi>Jacob</hi>'s
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62134:13"/>coming down into <hi>Egypt,</hi> with his whole Family, until his death, who dwelt in <hi>Egypt</hi> Seventeen years, and hence until <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s death, who dwelt in <hi>Egypt,</hi> an Hundred years wanting ſeven; in the Story hereof I find no evidence of Temples a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Egyptians. Nor from the birth of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was born (about Forty ſix years after the death of <hi>Levi,</hi> who was his Grandfather by the Mother, and great Grandfather by his Father) until his leading the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the ſpace of Fourſcore years, we find no mention of any Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or Temples there. You will ſay they had Gods, for the Lord ſaid, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.12. <hi>He would execute judgment upon all the gods of</hi> Egypt; and ſo it came to paſs, <hi>Numb.</hi> 33.4. But I anſwer, So <hi>Laban</hi> had his gods, which <hi>Rachel</hi> ſtole away from her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſate upon them to hide them from him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.30, 34. and in the days of <hi>Terah, Abraham</hi>'s Father, they ſerved o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gods: this we read; but of any Temples they had, we read not. If you ſay theſe gods that <hi>Terah</hi> and <hi>Laban</hi> had, were Houſhold gods, and ſome room in their private Houſes might ſerve for them, and for the Devotions performed unto them: but the gods of <hi>Egypt</hi> ſpoken of, were for Publick Uſe and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Service; and therefore they had their Prieſts alſo. To this I anſwer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pauſanius</hi> in <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiacis,</hi> p. 54.</note> That we read often in <hi>Pauſanius</hi> of <hi>Arae Jovis pluvij,</hi> which I underſtand of Images of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> ſtanding open with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any covering. <hi>And p.</hi> 58. he writes that in the Court of <hi>Priamus</hi> the Son of <hi>Laomedon,</hi> there ſtood the Image of <hi>Jupiter Paleus ſub Divo,</hi> under the open Heaven, and that to his Altar <hi>Priamus</hi> ſled when <hi>Troy</hi> was taken. And <hi>Alexander ab Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro</hi> writes, that the Houſe of <hi>Jupiter Pulverinus,</hi> in the Country of <hi>Attica,</hi> had no Roof, but was open above; this he hath in his ſecond Book of <hi>Genial Days,</hi> and <hi>Chap.</hi> 22. So the Image of <hi>Minerva Pavia</hi> was, <hi>ſab Divo,</hi> in the open Air, as <hi>Pauſanius</hi> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies in his <hi>Laconica, p.</hi> 90. &amp; 95. The ſame Author tells us, that in a ſmall Iſland were the brazen Figures of <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux, ſub Divo</hi> in the open Air, <hi>nibilo pedalibus majora</hi> of a foots length and no more; ſuch belike were the Puppets <hi>Rachel</hi> ſate upon, called <hi>Laban</hi>'s gods; and a number of ſuch he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth ſtanding in the open Air; and ſometimes he makes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of certain <hi>Delubra,</hi> Temples which had no Roof, but were open above towards the Heavens, as in his <hi>Boeoticis,</hi> p. 260. And p. 264. He makes mention of a Chappel of <hi>Ceres,</hi> ſirnamed <hi>Europa,</hi> where there is <hi>ſub Divo Jupiter pluvius,</hi> rainy <hi>Jupiter,</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:62134:13"/>ſtanding in the open Air. <hi>Coelius Rodigimus l.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 355. <hi>Jovi Fulguri, Soli, Lunae, Coelo, Hypaethra, id eſt ſubdialia conſtitui debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Templa proponimus.</hi> Add unto this <hi>ſubdiales ſtatuas Levit.</hi> 26.30. as <hi>Junius</hi> renders it. And having Altars at ſuch Images where they offered Sacrifices, no marvel if they had Prieſts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> we know, is called <hi>the Priest of the moſt High God,</hi> and <hi>King of Salem;</hi> but I do not think any Man will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch, that he had a Temple there. <hi>Abraham</hi> was a Prophet, <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. and was he not a Prieſt alſo? it is clear he offered Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. and <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 26. ſo <hi>Jacob,</hi> and that by God's commandment, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35. And whereas ſome are of opinion, that when <hi>Jacob</hi> vowed unto God the Tenth of all that God ſhould give him in <hi>Meſopotamia, Gen.</hi> 28. and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon a queſtion is moved, To whom he ſhould pay the Tenth of all, that is, to what Prieſt? knowing no better Anſwer, are of opinion that he paid it to himſelf, ſuppoſing him to be a Prieſt, and capable of receiving Tythes. I willingly confeſs ſuch a Devotion is very profitable as to Temporals: but I ſee no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity that caſts us upon ſuch conceits: For he might well Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice unto God the Tenth, or the worth of the Tenth, and all that he poſſeſſed. As yet the Prieſthood was not confined to one Family, and till then, <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf was a Prieſt as well as a Prophet, even to the erecting of the Tabernacle, which by Archb. <hi>Uſhers</hi> computation, was in the year of the World 1514. But let us proceed further, and take into conſideration what we find in profare Hiſtories concerning Temples.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Diodorus Siculus l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 1. reports, that in the opinion of ſome, the Ethiopians were the firſt of Men, and he gives reaſons for it, but in a moſt atheiſtical and unreaſonable way, feigning Men to have been <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> born of the Earth and Air, in a natural manner, as Mice and other things of equivocal Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And how this came to paſs, he proſecutes in a moſt abſurd and brain-ſick Diſcourſe, without taking notice of any Creator, <hi>who of one blood made all mankind to dwell upon the face of the earth.</hi> And adds, that the worſhip of God was firſt found out by them. <hi>Sacraque inſuper, pompas, celebritates, aliaque quibus diis honores impenduntur, ab iis fuiſſe reperta.</hi> And what manner of Gods muſt they needs be, who are worſhipped by thoſe who acknowledge no Creator? St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that <hi>the eternal power and Godhead is known from the Creation, conſidered in his works.</hi> His beſt proof for this is out of <hi>Homer,</hi> who brings in <hi>Jupiter,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62134:14"/>and the reſt of the Gods with him, going in Progreſs into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thopia,</hi> both to the Sacrifices there made unto them, and for the ſweetneſs of the odours there. And ſurely it is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous, that ſuch Gods as are deviſed by the fancies of Men, and made at their pleaſures, ſhould be well content to be ſerved and worſhipped according to the Fancies of Men, and at their plea ſure: for undoubtedly Man hath as much power to deviſe a Divine and Religious Worſhip, as to make a God; any Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice being good enough, and too good, to be beſtowed upon the work of their own hands, yea or upon their own Fancies either. Yet the truth is, there was a time when the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom of God's Church was pleaſed with bodily Sacrifices of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered with good hearty, and had his abode in the Mountains of Spices. <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.14. <hi>Make haſte my beloved, and be thou like unto a Roe, or to a young Hart upon the Mountains of Spices.</hi> But this was only for a time <hi>until the day did break, and the ſhadows fled away,</hi> Cant. 2.17. The Lord Chriſt now adays is the moſt ſweet ſmelling Savour, both to God the Father and us; by whom alone the Father is ſatisfied, and our Souls ſweetly refreſhed. Indeed I read that <hi>Heſiod</hi> and <hi>Homer,</hi> were <hi>Primi Deorum opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices apud Graecos,</hi> the firſt Crafts-maſters in coining Gods among the Grecians, in <hi>Herodotus lib.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 124. <hi>Graeco-Lat. Heſiodus atque Homerus, (qui quadringent is non amplius annis ante me extitere) fuere, qui Graecis Theogoniam introduxerunt, eiſque &amp; cognomina, &amp; honores, &amp; diverſa artificia, &amp; figuras attribuerunt.</hi> And p. 166. <hi>Ipſi Aegyptij extiterunt principes conventus, &amp; pompas &amp; concilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula factitandi, &amp; ab iis Graeci didicerunt. Cujus rei hoc apud me argumentum eſt, quod illa conſtet priſcis temporibus: Graecanica ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò recens fuiſſe inſtitua.</hi> And we know <hi>Homer</hi> lived after the Wars of <hi>Troy,</hi> ſome ſay 80 years, ſome 100, others 140, others 180 years after the taking of <hi>Troy.</hi> Nay, there are that make him 200 years, yea 240 later than that, yea ſome 400, others 500 later; as <hi>Talianus</hi> gives inſtance in ſeveral Authors, thus tar differing about the time of <hi>Homer,</hi> as any may read in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> his <hi>Evangelical Preparation, Book</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 492. <hi>Graeco-Lat.</hi> We by the Word of God are brought acquainted not only with the Creation of Man, but of the World alſo, and how in 1656. it was drowned, and all Fleſh periſhed by the Waters of a general Deluge, in whom was the breath of Life, except thoſe four couple, eight perſons in all, who were reſerved for a Seed to ſow the World anew, and preſerved in the Ark which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62134:14"/>ſetled in <hi>Ararat,</hi> commonly conceived to be a Mountain in <hi>Armenia</hi> (though ſome think otherwiſe) and from thoſe parts near adjoyning, and particularly from <hi>Babel,</hi> after the Conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Languages, began the diſperſion of the People. And as the Lord by his extraordinary Providence, provided both for the making of the Ark, and bringing all ſorts of Creatures thereinto, and maintenance for them, and their preſervation there, did make himſelf known unto them, (after a degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate time that came upon all) both as a God of Vengeance in deſtroying others, and alſo as a God of Mercy and Salvation in preſerving them from that common Deſtruction; promiſing withal never to deſtroy the World ſo again: ſo from them, and by them, was the knowledge of God propagated to their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; which about 101. years after the Flood, began to be diſperſed over all the World. And upon <hi>Nimrod</hi>'s Uſurpation, Rebel-like, his Nature anſwering to his Name, it ſeems that both his Father and Grandfather, and many of them ſeparated themſelves from him, <hi>Cuſh</hi> into <hi>Ethiopia, Miſraim</hi> into <hi>Egypt, Canaan</hi> into <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> where we find <hi>Sidon</hi> a principal City by the Sea. And as <hi>Egypt</hi> is called in Scripture the Land of <hi>Ham,</hi> ſo by as good reaſon <hi>Ethiopia</hi> alſo. <hi>Lydiat</hi> is of opinon concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Ham,</hi> that he was the eldeſt of <hi>Noah</hi>'s three Children; and by the younger Son of <hi>Noah, Gen.</hi> 9.24. is meant <hi>Canaan No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi>'s Grandchild; (for even our Grandchildren we count our Children) and <hi>Noah</hi>'s Curſe we know, paſſed not upon <hi>Ham,</hi> but upon <hi>Canaan:</hi> which makes it probable that the lewd prank which gave ſuch offence to <hi>Noah,</hi> and he ſound out by exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, was play'd by <hi>Canaan;</hi> and by him his Father <hi>Ham</hi> came to the knowledge of it, who told his two Brethren there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Japhet.</hi> And thus indeed the Egyptians and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thopians, and whole houſe of <hi>Ham,</hi> may be accounted the eld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Houſe of the World, if he were elder than his two Brethren <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Japhet.</hi> But in this <hi>Lydiat</hi> is almoſt alone, moſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors being for <hi>Sem,</hi> or <hi>Japhet</hi> (which is more likely) being the eldeſt, as may be ſeen at large in <hi>Uſher</hi>'s <hi>Chronol. Sacra. c.</hi> 4. <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> ſeparated towards the North, both Eaſt and Weſt, but chiefly towards the Weſt. <hi>Sem</hi>'s Poſterity continued in the Eaſt towards the South; <hi>Aſſur</hi> his Son having erected a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy in <hi>Niniveh.</hi> But as yet no teſtimony for Temples any where.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62134:15"/>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Diogines Laertius</hi> an approved Writer, in his fifth Book of the Lives of Philoſophers, in the Life of <hi>Epimenides,</hi> ſaith of him, That <hi>Conſtruxit apud Athenienſes phanum verendorum Deo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ut ait Lobon Argivns in libro de Poetis. Fertur etiam primus domus atque agros expiaſſe delubraque erexiſſe.</hi> This <hi>Epimenides</hi> of <hi>Crete</hi> built a Temple to the Gods, call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Dij reverends,</hi> ſome that deſerved to be reverenced (as he thought) more than all the pack, and he alledgeth <hi>Lobon</hi> of <hi>Argos,</hi> in his Book of Poets, teſtifying this. This <hi>Epimenides</hi> alſo is ſaid to have been the firſt that ſhewed a courſe for the expiation of Houſes and Fields, and that erected Temples. The expiation here ſpoken of, was by Sacrifice, as appears by the Story mentioned a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before: For having mentioned how the fame of this Man flying throughout all <hi>Grece,</hi> he was reputed a Man moſt dear to God; thereupon an Inſtance thereof is given thus: <hi>The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians were ſometimes viſited with a ſore Peſtilence, who thereupon asking counſel hereabouts, as their manner was, at the Oracle of</hi> Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos, Pythia <hi>the Nun Priest anſwered them, That the City of</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens <hi>was to be expiated. And they being ignorant, how this was to be performed, diſpatched</hi> Niceas <hi>the Son of</hi> Niceratus <hi>by Ship into the Iſland of</hi> Crete, <hi>to</hi> Epimenides, <hi>to intreat him to come over unto them. Upon their intreaty he came, and expiated or purged their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty after this manner: He took Sheep, ſome white ſome black, and brought them to</hi> Mars <hi>his Street, and there let them go whither they would, ſending ſome after them, to obſerve where they lay down; and whereſoever any of them lay down, there he gave charge they ſhould be ſacrificed</hi> peculiari cuipiam Deo, <hi>to ſome peculiar God. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſaith <hi>Laertius,</hi> to a fit God: his meaning was, to the God that plagued them; but who it was they knew not. And therefore <hi>Laertius</hi> addeth, That <hi>even in his days there were to be ſeen in the Streets of</hi> Athens, <hi>Altars without a Name, as a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of that expiation, and hereupon he ſaith that the Plague ceaſed.</hi> And in all likelyhood the Altar that St. <hi>Paul</hi> obſerved as he went in one of the Streets of <hi>Athens</hi> with this Inſcription, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to the unknown God, was one of thoſe Altars <hi>Laertius</hi> writes of, though the Inſcription might be defaced in his days; for in <hi>Cauſabon</hi>'s judgment, <hi>Laertius</hi> lived not until the year 200. after Chriſt, that is about the time of <hi>Tertullian;</hi> yet Altars with ſuch Inſcriptions were nothing ſtrange; ſuch a one being mentioned by <hi>Pauſanias</hi> in his <hi>Eliacks, p.</hi> 162. <hi>Adjacet ei ignoto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Deorum ara.</hi> Now this <hi>Epimenides</hi> came to <hi>Athens</hi> about this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62134:15"/>buſineſs, by <hi>Laertius</hi>'s accompt in the 47th <hi>Olympiad,</hi> and others reckon him to be coaetaneus to <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> who lived in the time of <hi>Servius Tullus,</hi> the fifth King of <hi>Rome</hi> from <hi>Romulus.</hi> Now <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf had its Foundation laid, but in the days of <hi>Jotham</hi> King of <hi>Judab,</hi> by <hi>Lydiat</hi> and Uſher</hi>'s accompt, and the very year after <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> had inchoated his Kingdom of <hi>Babylon,</hi> which was a Type of Romiſh <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>Janus</hi> was a King in <hi>Italy</hi> long before <hi>Romulus;</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, a certain Writer, <hi>Xenon</hi> by name, in the firſt Book of his <hi>Italica,</hi> aſcribes the firſt building of Temples, as <hi>Macrobius</hi> teſtifies in the firſt Book of his <hi>Saturnals, Chap.</hi> 9. Now the beginning of <hi>Janus</hi> his Latin Kingdom, <hi>Lydiat</hi> reckons to be 150 years, before <hi>Aeneas</hi> his coming into <hi>Italy</hi> in the days of <hi>Latinus,</hi> the fifth King after <hi>Janus; Aeneas</hi> his arriving there being the third year after the taking of <hi>Troy,</hi> which yet by <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat</hi>'s accompt was 60 years after the death of <hi>Othniel,</hi> the firſt Judge of <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the death of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and 120 years after the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s coming out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Now this <hi>Janus</hi> was the Man that entertained old <hi>Saturn,</hi> when he fled from his Son <hi>Jupiter</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> and admitted him <hi>in Societatem Regni,</hi> to reign with him. Thence <hi>Italy</hi> came to be called <hi>Latium,</hi> as <hi>Ovid</hi> Writes, ſaying,
<q>Et dicta est Latium terra latente Deo.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Virgil</hi> in his <hi>Aeneids</hi> 8.
<q>
                     <l>Primus ab aethereo veniens Saturnus Olympo,</l>
                     <l>Arma Jovis fugiens, &amp; Regnis exul adentis;</l>
                     <l>Is genus indocile, ac diſperſum montibus altis</l>
                     <l>Compoſuit, legeſque dedit Latiumque vocari</l>
                     <l>Maluit, his quoniam latuiſſet tutus in Oris.</l>
                  </q>
where I obſerve the Poet's wiſdom, affecting to grace his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; for he feigns <hi>Saturn</hi> not to come thither flying from the Iſle of <hi>Crete,</hi> but from Heaven forſooth, to ſalve the Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Deity, and the Honour of his own Country; and adds, that his days were the time of that golden Age of the World, as <hi>Ovid</hi> and other Poets feign: His words are theſe;
<q>Aureaque, ut perhibent, illo ſub Rege fuere.</q>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:62134:16"/>In the days of <hi>Saturn</hi> was the golden Age of the World. Now this fairly may revive the remembrance of a Note made by <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> upon a Paſſage in Virgil, deſcribing the goodly Temple that Queen <hi>Dido</hi> was building, when <hi>Aeneas,</hi> after the taking of <hi>Troy,</hi> came thither, being caſt by a Tempeſt upon thoſe Parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Hic Templum Junoni ingens Sidonia Dido</l>
                     <l>Condebat, donis opulentum &amp; numine Divae:</l>
                     <l>Aerea cui gradibus ſurgebant limina, nexaeque</l>
                     <l>Aerc trabes foribus cardo ſtridebat ahenis.</l>
                  </q>
Now whereas <hi>Virgil</hi> hath <hi>aerea limina,</hi> brazen Threſholds, <hi>Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> maketh a queſtion of the reaſon why he calls the Threſhold brazen; it ſeeming unlikly that they ſhould be made of, or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with Braſs: his anſwer is, That <hi>Virgil</hi> delivers it, <hi>alluſione facta ad Saecula tunc temporis aerea,</hi> in alluſion to the condition of thoſe times, the brazen Age being then on foot. Though for ought I ſee, it might go for an Iron Age well enough, when ſuch ado was made in the World, ſuch Wars raiſed for 10 years continuance at <hi>Troy,</hi> and all for the Recovery of a Whore, if it be a true Hiſtory, and not a Poetical Fiction, as ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. In thoſe days there were Temples, I nothing doubt, and before; for the Trojans had theirs, as the ſame <hi>Virgil</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the perſon of <hi>Aeneas,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Nos delubra Deum miſeri quibus ultimus eſſet,</l>
                     <l>Ille dies feſta velamus fronde per urbem.</l>
                  </q>
we poor Creatures made that day, a Feſtival day in our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; which alas was to be our laſt day, their Funeral follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing immediately after. And not in the brazen Age only can we well admit that Temples have been, but in the golden Age alſo, as namely in the days of <hi>Saturn,</hi> which yet will be found 160 years after the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s coming out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And if <hi>Saturn</hi> were the chief of Heathen Deities, ſurely <hi>Moſes</hi> is much more ancient than they all; how much more anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent than Temples made to them. It is true <hi>Cicero</hi> makes menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of three <hi>Jupiters,</hi> one the Son of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Ops</hi> King of <hi>Crete,</hi> whoſe Sepulchre is there found; which <hi>Callimachus</hi> is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient to hear, and therefore brands them for lyars, ſaying,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62134:16"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </q>
The Cretians are always lyars, for they have built a Sepulchre to thee, O King, whereas thou dieſt not, but liveſt for ever-The other two, <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, were born in <hi>Areadia;</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the one <hi>Aether,</hi> of whom came <hi>Proſerpina</hi> and <hi>Liber,</hi> or <hi>Bacchus;</hi> the Father of the other <hi>Coelum,</hi> and he begat <hi>Miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va.</hi> In like ſort <hi>Japetus</hi> is ſaid by <hi>Heſiod</hi> to be the Son of <hi>Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum &amp; Terrae,</hi> of Heaven and Earth; as much as to ſay, they could not tell who was the Father of them, and therefore they feigned them to have been brought forth by the Heaven and Earth, and Sea and Rivers. But <hi>Virgil</hi> confounds theſe <hi>Jupiters</hi> which <hi>Cicero</hi> diſtinguiſheth, and feigns <hi>Saturn</hi> the Father of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter Cretenſis</hi> to have come <hi>ab Aethereo Olympo,</hi> that is, from from <hi>Aether</hi> and <hi>Heaven.</hi> And <hi>Japetus</hi> we ſee how plainly it ſounds <hi>Japhet,</hi> one of the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi> as <hi>Mercer</hi> upon <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and many others obſerve. And as <hi>Heſiod</hi> relates very ſtrange things of <hi>Saturns</hi> dealing with his Father <hi>Coelum;</hi> ſo the Jewiſh Rabbins relate as ſtrange things (yea the very ſame) of <hi>Ham's</hi> dealing with his Father, ſuppoſing they have ſome ground for it in the Scripture. And ſure we are, that <hi>Noah</hi> himſelf had no Children after the Flood, and this <hi>Ham</hi> was <hi>Japhet</hi>'s Brother; and both better known to the World than their Father <hi>Noah,</hi> who with his Son <hi>Sem</hi> (as it ſeems) lived a private life; whilſt his Children, and Childrens children divided the World among them, calling the ſeveral Regions of it, after their own Names, and erecting Monarchies; <hi>Nimrod</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Aſſur</hi> at <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niveh. Horace</hi> makes mention of <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dax Japeti genus,</hi> his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity were bold Creatures, that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt venture in a Ship to make a way through the Sea, which fairly refers to the Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Japhet,</hi> of whoſe Children, the Iſles of the Gentiles were divided in their Lands, <hi>every one after his tongue,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 10.5.</note> and <hi>after their Families in their Nations.</hi> And all the three Sons of <hi>Noah</hi> it's likely were imployed by their Father, in building the Ark; and by them their Poſterity might eaſily be inſtructed in that Art, the Lord himſelf firſt inſtructing <hi>Noah.</hi> Eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering how long both <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Sem</hi> lived after the Flood: <hi>Noah</hi> 350 years, that is, not only after the <hi>Babylonian</hi> and <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Kingdoms erected by <hi>Nimrod</hi> and <hi>Aſſur,</hi> 235 years; but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62134:17"/>after the Poſterity of <hi>Miſraim</hi> began to reign in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Principalities, 89 years; and after <hi>Ogyges</hi> built <hi>Thebes</hi> in <hi>Grece,</hi> 41 years; and after <hi>Aegialeus</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Sicyonians</hi> in <hi>Peloponneſus</hi> his beginning to reign, 23 years; and died but two or three years before <hi>Abraham</hi> was born. And <hi>Sem</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved 150 years after his Father <hi>Noah;</hi> and <hi>Sem</hi> died but 10 years before <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were born, according to <hi>Lydiat</hi>'s Chronicle, which I take to be moſt accurate. And for ought I know to the contrary, both <hi>Ham</hi> and <hi>Japhet,</hi> might live as long as <hi>Sem,</hi> and the Grecians, and Iſles of the Gentiles, might be well known to be <hi>Japeti genus.</hi> Though I deny not but others of his Poſterity might be called by his name, like as we read of two Kings of <hi>Athens,</hi> each called by the name of <hi>Cecrops,</hi> the one of <hi>Cecrops major,</hi> and the other of <hi>Cecrops mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor;</hi> and the younger of them divers Ages after the elder. And the name of <hi>Iphitus,</hi> who was but one Age before the Wars of <hi>Troy,</hi> doth plainly carry the ſame Radical Letters that <hi>Japetus</hi> doth. But to proceed.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The Pelaſgians are accounted by <hi>Strabo</hi> in his fifth Book, <hi>Populi Graeciae vetuſtiſſimi,</hi> the moſt ancient People of <hi>Greece.</hi> And theſe He and <hi>Heſiod,</hi> and <hi>Pauſanias</hi> in his <hi>Arcadicis,</hi> teſtifie to have proceeded from <hi>Pelaſgus. Ac primum omnium Pelaſgum memorant Arcadi in illa terra extitiſſe;</hi> The Arcadians report, that <hi>Pelaſgus</hi> was the firſt of Men in that Country: which rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Pauſanias</hi> modifies thus, That he was the firſt King there, to wit, in <hi>Arcadiae;</hi> and who firſt brought the rude People there, to build Cottages, to defend themſelves from the Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Weather. <hi>Lycaon</hi> was his Son, and him <hi>Pauſanias</hi> makes coetaneous to <hi>Cecrops,</hi> meaning <hi>Cecrops major,</hi> which <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crops</hi> is commonly accounted coetaneous with <hi>Moſes;</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his Tenth Book of his <hi>Evangelical Preparation, Chap.</hi> 19. and he adds this as a thing confeſſed by all, <hi>Nemo non fatetur. Lycanon</hi>'s youngeſt Son was <hi>Oenotrius,</hi> who went with a Colony into <hi>Italy,</hi> and from him that Country of <hi>Italy</hi> was called <hi>Oenotria.</hi> Yet there were no <hi>Temples</hi> till the days of <hi>Janus</hi> by the Teſtimony of <hi>Xenon</hi> formerly mentioned, out of <hi>Macrobius</hi> his <hi>Saturnals, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. And this was the firſt of all the Grecian Colonies in the opinion of <hi>Pauſanias;</hi> and he adds alſo, That neither had he found any Tranſmigration made by the Barbarians before this. But therein we know <hi>Pauſanias</hi> miſtakes, and that <hi>Grece</hi> and all <hi>Europe,</hi> after the Univerſal De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62134:17"/>was firſt inhabited by thoſe of the Poſterity of <hi>Noah,</hi> and ſpecially of <hi>Japhet,</hi> who came into the Weſtern Parts from the Eaſt. And the <hi>Iones,</hi> a People ſo well known both in <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſs, and in <hi>Grece,</hi> do fairly manifeſt by their very Name, that they were deſcended from <hi>Javan,</hi> one of the Sons of <hi>Japhet.</hi> Now <hi>Janus,</hi> the firſt erector of Temples in <hi>Italy,</hi> was near about 200 years after <hi>Cecrops</hi> began firſt to reign in the Region of <hi>Attica.</hi> Yet I confeſs that <hi>Jupiter</hi> is ſaid to have gotten <hi>Lyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>'s Daughter, <hi>Caliſto,</hi> with Child; and beſides <hi>Jupiter</hi> of <hi>Grece, Cicero</hi> makes mention of two <hi>Jupiters</hi> born in <hi>Arcadia;</hi> I doubt one of them might be <hi>Lycaon</hi>'s Brother, for ſuch inceſtuous Generations were too too frequent amongſt thoſe Heathen called Gods.</p>
               <p n="12">12. But conſider we what <hi>Pauſanias</hi> writes in his <hi>Eliacis pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oribus</hi> of <hi>Saturn, Saturnum primum omnium Coeli Regnum obtinuiſſe.</hi> That Saturn firſt of all obtained the Kingdom of <hi>Coelum,</hi> which we commonly render Heaven; but it might be the name of a Country in <hi>Crete,</hi> like as <hi>Olympia</hi> was a Country in <hi>Grece,</hi> where the hill <hi>Olympus</hi> was, which word <hi>Olympus</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly uſed by Poets to ſignifie Heaven. <hi>Ei in Olympia ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines eos (quod aureum genus nuncupatum eſt) Templum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicaſſe;</hi> To him the Men of the golden Age dedicated a Temple in <hi>Olympia.</hi> After this <hi>Jupiter</hi> being born, his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther committed him to the <hi>Dactyles</hi> of <hi>Ida</hi> to be kept; theſe were four Brethren, of whom <hi>Hercules,</hi> called <hi>Idaeus,</hi> was one, long before <hi>Hercules</hi> the Son of <hi>Amphytruo.</hi> This <hi>Hercules</hi> as the ſame <hi>Pauſanias</hi> writes, was great Grandfather to <hi>Clymenus,</hi> who coming out of <hi>Crete,</hi> firſt inſtituted the <hi>Olympian</hi> Games, 50 years after <hi>Deucalion</hi>'s Flood. Now if we accompt 30 years to an Age, as <hi>Lydiat</hi> doth, and that according to <hi>Clemens Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus,</hi> if I miſtake not; and that <hi>Clymenus</hi> was 30 years old at the inſtitution of theſe <hi>Olympian</hi> Games, from thence to the Birth of <hi>Hercules,</hi> the ſum of years ariſeth but to 120. Now by <hi>Lydiat</hi>'s accompt <hi>Moſes</hi> led the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> but 30 years after <hi>Deucalion</hi>'s Flood; that is, 30 years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Clymenus</hi> his inſtitution, at what time <hi>Moſes</hi> was 80 years old. Hence it follows, that <hi>Hercules</hi> was not born above 20 years before <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor this <hi>Saturn</hi> neither. For that <hi>Hercules</hi> to whom the tutalidge of <hi>Jupiter</hi> was committed, might well be as old as <hi>Saturn</hi> himſelf, yet this <hi>Hercules Idaeus</hi> had his name from the Hill <hi>Ida</hi> in <hi>Crete;</hi> and therefore in all likelyhood <hi>Saturn</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:62134:18"/>his Father, was the ſame that fled into <hi>Italy,</hi> and there was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by <hi>Janus,</hi> many years after <hi>Moſes.</hi> And whereas <hi>Pauſanias</hi> gives much credit to <hi>Homer</hi> concerning Matters of <hi>Grece,</hi> why ſhould we not give as much credit to <hi>Virgil</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Story of <hi>Italy?</hi> Yet that of <hi>Saturn</hi>'s Entertainment by <hi>Janus</hi> is a Story very commonly received. Yet I confeſs <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus Siculus</hi> makes mention of a <hi>Saturn,</hi> and a <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and an <hi>Hercules,</hi> and <hi>Curetes Dactyli</hi> in <hi>Phrygia;</hi> but upon what ground I know not, for <hi>Pauſanias</hi> doth not; and it ſeems from <hi>Curetes</hi> by Contraction came <hi>Cretes,</hi> and thence that Iſland of <hi>Crete</hi> might have his Name; but I ſtand not upon this: Nay, I yield rather that it had its Name from one <hi>Cres,</hi> who reigned there at the ſame time that <hi>Inachus</hi> reigned at <hi>Argos</hi> in <hi>Grece.</hi> It may be then the <hi>Curetes</hi> were the ſame with <hi>Cretes.</hi> But it is nothing ſtrange the <hi>Grecians</hi> ſhould be found to run wild ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in their Accounts of times, conſidering that <hi>Cadmus</hi> was the firſt, who coming out of <hi>Phoenicia</hi> to <hi>Thebes,</hi> taught <hi>Greeks</hi> the uſe of Letters, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> writes in his <hi>Evangelical Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. and <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> in the firſt Book of his <hi>Stromata, p.</hi> 306. <hi>Graeco-lat.</hi> Though I know <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> minceth the matter, ſaying that he brought amongſt them only a new Character, belike for the Honour of the Greek Nation, being loth that the World ſhould take notice that they were beholden to the <hi>Phoenicians</hi> for this.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Before I have ſhewed out of <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> that ſuch Structures as were firſt the Sepulchres of the Dead, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, being enlarged to a greater Magnificence, came to be called the Temples of gods: And <hi>Arnobius, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Quid quod multa ex his templa quae Tholis ſunt aureis, &amp; ſublimibus elata faſtigiis auctorum conſcriptionibus comprobatur, contegere cineres at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> oſſa &amp; defunctorum eſſe corporum ſepulchra. Nonne patet &amp; in promtu eſt, aut pro Diis immortalibus mortuos vos colere, aut inexpiabilem fieri numinibus contumeliam, quorum delubra &amp; templa, mortuorum ſuperlata ſunt buſtis?</hi> What ſhall we ſay to this, that many Temples which are built with golden Arches and lofty Roofs, do cover Aſhes and Bones, and that they are the Sepulchres of Men deceaſed, as it appears by the Writings of divers Authors? Is it not manifeſt and prone to conclude hereby, that either you worſhip dead Men inſtead of gods, or that you do the gods an Injury that cannot be expiated, in that you build their Temples upon the Sepulchres of the dead? Now the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62134:18"/>given in this kind by <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> in his <hi>Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to the Gentiles,</hi> I find to be of the Temple of <hi>Minerva,</hi> which was the Sepulchre of <hi>Acriſius.</hi> Now this <hi>Acriſius</hi> was the 14th King of <hi>Argos,</hi> by the Account of <hi>Appion</hi> the Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, alledged by <hi>Tatianus,</hi> and repreſented by <hi>Enſebius,</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th Book of his <hi>Evangelical Preparation, p.</hi> 493. <hi>Graecolat.</hi> And in the Fourth Generation after <hi>Danaus,</hi> who came out of <hi>Egypt</hi> unto <hi>Argos</hi> in <hi>Grece,</hi> upon the Confuſion cauſed in <hi>Egypt,</hi> partly by the Slaughter of the Firſt Born, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Deſtruction of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his <hi>Egyptians</hi> in the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> when <hi>Moſes</hi> led the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> through it, towards the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> by the Account of Mr. <hi>Lydiat</hi> in his <hi>Emendation of Times.</hi> And that which <hi>Appion</hi> writeth hereof, was out of <hi>Piolimaeus Mendeſius. Pauſanias</hi> in his <hi>Boeoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> ſpeaks of a Temple dedicated to <hi>Hercules;</hi> but whereas ſome imagine, or might imagine that it was a Temple dedicated to <hi>Hercules,</hi> the Son of <hi>Amphytrion,</hi> he profeſſeth that it was <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vetuſtius,</hi> much more ancient than ſo; and therefore he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives rather, the Dedication of it ought to be aſcribed to a more ancient <hi>Hercules,</hi> who was one of the <hi>Idaei Dactyli,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Hercules Idaeus.</hi> Now theſe <hi>Idaei Dactyli</hi> were thoſe <hi>Curetes</hi> to whoſe Care the Education of <hi>Jupiter</hi> was committed; to wit, <hi>Jupiter Cretenſis,</hi> the Son of <hi>Saturn,</hi> who flying out of <hi>Crete</hi> and coming into <hi>Italy,</hi> was there entertained by <hi>Janus;</hi> which <hi>Janus</hi> reigned in <hi>Italy</hi> long after <hi>Moſes,</hi> as formerly hath been ſhewed. The ſame <hi>Pauſanias</hi> in the firſt of his <hi>Eliacks,</hi> affirms, <hi>Pelops</hi> was the firſt that erected a Temple to <hi>Mercury</hi> in <hi>Peloponneſus;</hi> and in his <hi>Boeoticis</hi> reports that one <hi>Myron By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zantius,</hi> a Writer of Heroick Verſes and Elegies, had deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>Amphyon</hi> was the firſt of all Men that dedicated an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar to <hi>Mercury.</hi> Now <hi>Pelops</hi> is accounted but of the ſame time with <hi>Acriſius</hi> King of <hi>Argos,</hi> the Fourth King after <hi>Danaus,</hi> by <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his <hi>Evangelical Preparation, lib.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 493. <hi>Graecolar.</hi> And the ſame <hi>Tatianus</hi> in the ſame place of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> maintains <hi>Moſes</hi> to have been before <hi>Amphyon.</hi> But of all the Temples known to <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> the moſt Ancient he profeſſeth to have been the Temple of <hi>Apollo Thearius,</hi> which was the <hi>Troeze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians.</hi> For albeit he takes notice of two other Temples which were very ancient; yet this, he ſaith, was much more ancient than they, and was reported to have been built by <hi>Pythius,</hi> and as it was built by him, ſo it was adorned by him alſo. Now
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:62134:19"/>what time <hi>Pythius</hi> lived, he ſheweth forthwith, when he ſaith, that <hi>Bellerophon</hi> coming to <hi>Troezene,</hi> where <hi>Pithias</hi> reigned, he required of him <hi>Aethra</hi> to be given him to Wife; but <hi>Aegeus</hi> married her King of <hi>Athens,</hi> and ſhe became the Mother of <hi>Theſous,</hi> as <hi>Robert Stephanus</hi> writes; and <hi>Pellerophon</hi> was deprived of his Kingdom of <hi>Ephyra</hi> by <hi>Praetos</hi> King of <hi>Argos,</hi> as the ſame Author writeth. Now this <hi>Praetus</hi> was the third King of <hi>Argos</hi> after <hi>Danaus,</hi> by <hi>Tatianus</hi> his account related by <hi>Euſebius, Praeparat. Evangel. lib.</hi> 10. and <hi>Danaus</hi> is by <hi>Lidiat</hi>'s Account ſomewhat after <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. But we proceed from the <hi>Grecians</hi> to the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſuppoſed by ſome to have found out and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to others, the Names of Heatheniſh Gods, and firſt erected Temples and Altars to them, for ſo writes <hi>Caelius Rodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginus, l.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 37. <hi>Traditur porro Aegyptios primos Deorum exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe aras, conflaſſe ſimulacra, &amp; Templa conſtruxiſſe:</hi> But this learned Antiquary (which is his uſual fault) tells us not his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. Probably <hi>Herodotus, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Aegiptii primi &amp; Deorum cognomina in uſu habuere, &amp; ab illis Graeci fuerunt mutuati. Item primi Diis &amp; aras, &amp; ſimulachra &amp; delubra ſtatuere.</hi> And <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanias</hi> in his <hi>Atticis</hi> teſtifies, that amongſt the <hi>Grecians,</hi> the <hi>Athenians</hi> went beyond all others in Devotion towards the Gods. <hi>Athenienſes Deorum cultu, ſtudioque Religionis longè caeteras omnes civitates anteire:</hi> And the Athenians had this from their King <hi>Cerops major,</hi> as <hi>Lidiat</hi> writes, <hi>Emend. temp. p.</hi> 18. <hi>Erat vero etiam Cecrops Magnus auctor ſuperſtitionis ac Idololatriae.</hi> This <hi>Cecrops</hi> was called <hi>Diphyes,</hi> becauſe he was <hi>genere partim Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius;</hi> by Parentage an Egyptian, and <hi>Coquaeus</hi> out of <hi>Euſebius</hi> relates this of <hi>Cecrops,</hi> That <hi>primus Jovem appellavit, ſimulacra re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periit, aram ſtatuit, victimas immolavit, nequaquam iſtiuſmodi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in Graecia viſis, Coqu. in Auguſtin. de Civit. Dei, l.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Porphyry,</hi> that enemy of the Goſpel, was wont much to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify a certain Hiſtorian named <hi>Sanconiatho:</hi> His Hiſtory was much commended by one <hi>Philo Biblius,</hi> who added a Preface thereunto, wherein he writes, <hi>Barbarorum Antiquiſſimi Phoenices imprimis &amp; Aegyptii, (a quibus caeteri deinceps populi morem illum accepere) in maximorum Deorum loco eos omnes habuere, qui res ad vit am agendam neceſſarias inveniſſent, qui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> beneficium aliquod in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus humanum contuliſſent. Eos nimirum, quod ſibi plurimorum bonorum autores eſſe perſuaderent, Divinis honoribus coluere; ac tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorum uſu, quae jam ante conſtructa fuerant, hoc ad munus officium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:62134:19"/>traducto; columnas inſuper ſtatuaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ligne as ipſorum nomine conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, eo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> precipue religionis cultu proſecuti; feſtos illis quoque dies longè celeberrimos dedicarunt. In quo eximium illud fuit, Regum ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum nomina univerſi hujus elementis, ac quibuſdam corum quibus divinitatem ipſi tribuebant imponerent. Naturales vero Deos Solem, Lumam, reliquaſque Stellase errantes, cum Elementis &amp; caeteris cum ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſdem affinitate conjunctis, ſolos ex omnibus agnoſcebant; ut morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les quidem alios, alios autem immortales cos haberent.</hi> Where ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve four things: 1. That the firſt Founders of Idolatry are noted to be <hi>Phoenicians</hi> and <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who were the poſterity of <hi>Ham</hi> by <hi>Miſraim</hi> and <hi>Canaan.</hi> 2. That Temples were not at firſt built for the Gods, but having been formerly built for other uſes, were afterward turned to this uſe; and if you ask for what uſe they were at firſt built, I have nothing to anſwer but that of <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> namely, that they were at firſt built for ſome great Perſons to lie interr'd in after their deceaſe. 3. That the firſt Gods adored by them, which he calls natural Gods, were the Lights of Heaven, eſpecially the Planets and the Elements; all which makes up the number of eleven, and they had but twelve in all; now who might the Twelfth be? was he the firſt mover of all? <hi>Ariſtottle</hi> I am ſure, ſo inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preteth the Divinity of his Forefathers, as if by Sun and Moon, and the reſt of the Planets, they meant thoſe pure Minds which he calleth Intelligences; and whom he conceived to be the Movers of theſe Orbs; but withal he acknowledgeth a firſt Mover, in the Contemplation of whom the Perfection of all the reſt conſiſted. That was his Device by his Philoſophy to make the beſt conſtruction he could of the religious ways of his Anceſtors. But might not <hi>Pan</hi> be one of their Deities, and that a principal one? yet this ſeems to denote the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe: For it is too too true, that ſoon they fell away from the Acknowledgement of the Creator to worſhip the Creature. And <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith <hi>Praeparat. Evangel. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>That as</hi> Orpheus <hi>took his Diſcourſe of the Gods from the Doctrine of the Egyptians; ſo he would have the world to be God, compounded of many Gods, according to the ſeveral parts of the World. Laſtly,</hi> They came about to worſhip their deceaſed Anceſtors with religious Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And might not theſe be repreſented by the Images of thoſe Beaſts which were conſecrated by them? This ſurely is one ſpecial Interpretation, which <hi>Diodorus Siculus</hi> makes of thoſe Beaſts, which were ſo religiouſly, or ſuperſtitiouſly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:62134:20"/>eſteemed and reverenced by the Egyptians. And <hi>Dioge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Laertius,</hi> concerning the Devotion of the Egyptians this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way, ſaith in the Proem to his Book of the Lives of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, <hi>Statuas praeterea &amp; fana a ſe fabricari fatentur quod ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norent effigiem Dei:</hi> They make Images and Temples becauſe they know not the Shane of God. <hi>Ganſabon,</hi> though he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth the Sentence to be defective, yet he perſecteth it only thus; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they make Images and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to them, that is, to the bruit Creatures which they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, becauſe the Images of God they could not, foraſmuch as they knew not the Shape of God. And indeed, <hi>no man hath ſeen God at any time, Joh.</hi> 1.18. No, not God's own People, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.37. <hi>Ye have not heard God at any time, nor ſeen His ſhape,</hi> He is commended unto us as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the inviſible God, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.27 <hi>Thales Mileſius</hi> was reputed wiſe in his time, <hi>Diogenes Laertius</hi> writes that he had no Maſter, <hi>Niſi quod AEgyptiis Sacerdotibus, cò profectus, familiariter adbaeſit:</hi> He was very familiar with the Egyptian Prieſts. Himſelf profeſſeth as much in his Epiſtle to <hi>Phericides;</hi> and I willingly conſeſs two things were delivered by him concerning God very wiſely; the one concerning his Providence, for being demanded, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Man doing Evil might be hid from God, made this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Ne Cogitans quidem,</hi> No not ſo much as touching his Thought. The other concerning the Nature of God: For being demanded what God was, he made this Anſwer, <hi>Quod initio &amp; fine caret;</hi> That which is without beginning and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. And indeed thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to deſcribe the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head; namely, by his Eternal Power, when he ſaith, <hi>The eternal Power and Godhead hath been known from the Creation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſidered in his Works,</hi> Rom. 1.20. And <hi>Bradwardine</hi> maintains that the firſt Attribute of the Divine Nature is <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe Eſſe,</hi> of Neceſſary Being; as much as to ſay, Eternal, without Beginning and without End. Add to this what <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> writes, <hi>Evang. Preparat. l.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 451. <hi>Graecolat. Athenienſes Aegyptiorum Coloniam habitos eſſe, cum alii tum Theopompus in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>careno confirmat:</hi> That the Athenians were a Colony of the Egyptians, both others and alſo <hi>Theopompus</hi> confirms in his Book entituled <hi>Tricarenum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. Come we then to the Egyptians: Now <hi>Euſebius</hi> alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the former Paſſage out of <hi>Philo Biblius</hi> his Preface to <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coniatho,</hi> to prove that at the firſt, the very Heathens had no
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:62134:20"/>other Gods, but the very Stars and Planets appearing and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the Heavens: And that the Name of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (God) at the firſt was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a currendo,</hi> from moving or running, the Planets and Stars compaſſing all in the Courſe of Twenty Four Hours. He adds, that the very Scriptures do juſtifie this, ſhewing what was the Courſe of Gentiles in their Religious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions; namely, to worſhip the whole Hoſte of Heaven: And we know what Leſſon the Lord reads to his own People, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Take heed lest thou lift up thine eyes to Heaven, and when thou ſeeſt the Sun, and the Moon, and the Stars, with all the Hoſte of Heaven, ſhouldſt be driven to worſhip them, and to ſerve them; which the Lord thy God hath diſtributed to all people that are under the whole Heaven.</hi> As much as to ſay, the Lord hath made them thy Servants: Nay, the Servants of all Men under the Cope of Heaven; therefore take heed thou beeſt not carried away in the Courſe of Heatheniſh Blindneſs and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, as to make them thy Lords and thy Gods. In the ſame place the Lord gives them a Caveat, and admoniſheth them that they corrupt not themſelves, and make not a graven Image, or repreſentation of any Figure, whether it be the Likeneſs of Male or Female, the Likeneſs of any Beaſt that is on Earth, or Likeneſs of any feathered Foule, or the Likeneſs of any Fiſh that is in the Waters beneath the Earth; which gives ſhrewd Preſumption, that ſome ſuch Creatures were worſhipped among the Egyptians from whence they came, or in the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> whither they were traveling. And <hi>Euſebius, Prepara. Evangel. l.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 49. <hi>Graecolat.</hi> Reherſing out of <hi>Diodorus Sicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> the ſeveral Creatures which were conſecrated by the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, makes mention of <hi>Apis</hi> and <hi>Muevis Sacri Tauri,</hi> holy Bulls, and of <hi>Bosfemina</hi> a Cow; as alſo of Sheep; yea, of the Goat, and Dog, and the Wolfe, and the Cat; and amongſt Birds, of <hi>Ibis,</hi> and the Hawke, and the Eagle, and of the Crocadile that lives in the Waters: And that it was a capital Crime among them to kill any of theſe. And <hi>p.</hi> 52. he adds out of the ſame <hi>Diodorus,</hi> that the Grecians Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy began from <hi>Cadmus,</hi> whom he ſaith to have been after the days of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and that he ſaith may be clearly and evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirmed; and hence concludes that all the Gods of the Grecians were brought to light after the Days of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:62134:21"/>
               <p>But concerning the Antiquity of Temples among the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, <hi>Diogenes Laertius</hi> in the Life of <hi>Cleobulus</hi> writes, that he was of <hi>Lindus,</hi> or as ſome ſaid, of <hi>Carea,</hi> and that he reſtored the Temple of <hi>Minerva</hi> built by <hi>Danars;</hi> the Paſſage is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what imperfect, but made compleat by <hi>Cauſabon,</hi> with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that which <hi>Diodorus Siculur</hi> writes, <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. where he writes, <hi>Danaus ex Aegypto cum filiabus aufugiens in Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diam Cypri appulit, ſuſceptuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ab incolis, erecto Minervae Templo, ſtatuam ingentem dedicavit.</hi> He adds, that <hi>Cadmus</hi> about the ſame time being ſent to Sea to ſeek <hi>Europa,</hi> did perform his Vows at the ſame Temple: Now <hi>Lidiat</hi> accounts <hi>Cadmus</hi> his leaving <hi>Phaenicia</hi> and ſailing into <hi>Grece,</hi> to have been at the ſame time that <hi>Joſhua</hi> entered the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> with his If<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclites, and on the ſame occaſion, affrighted with the Invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made by <hi>Joſhua;</hi> and that <hi>Danaus</hi> his Expulſion out of <hi>Egypt</hi> by his Brother <hi>Aegyptus,</hi> was originally derived from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion that was brought upon the Land, by reaſon of the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Firſt Born among them, and the Deſtruction of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> and his Hoſte in the Red Sea. And in all likelihood this brought great Conſuſion in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and amongſt the Seed Royal, whereupon fore Contentions might ariſe, the iſſue whereof was as ſome prevailed, ſo the expulſion of the Oppoſites: <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptus</hi> himſelf being driven out afterwards, as he had been a means of driving out <hi>Danaus</hi> before. For ſo <hi>Pauſanias</hi> writes in <hi>Achiacis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Patrae <hi>and</hi> Aroe <hi>are all one.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Aegyptum Aroenveniſſe tradunt Patrenſes filiorum luctu confectum cum ipſum Argorum nomen exhorreſceret, &amp; imprimis à Danao ſibi plurimum metneret.</hi> And after this there were two Temples of <hi>Serapis</hi> built, and in one of them was erected a Monument of <hi>Aegyptus</hi> the Son of <hi>Belut. Herodotus</hi> aſcribes the building of this Temple at <hi>Lindus</hi> to <hi>Danaus</hi> his Daughters, about the end of his Second Book. And whereas <hi>Diodorus Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus</hi> reports the Temple to have been built in the Iſland of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus, Stephanus Bizantinus</hi> acknowledgeth no other City of <hi>Lindins</hi> or <hi>Lindia,</hi> but that at <hi>Rhodes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his 9th. Book of his <hi>Prepar. Evangel.</hi> and <hi>cb.</hi> 23. Writes, that two Temples, one at <hi>Athens,</hi> another at <hi>Heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opolis</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> were built by the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the time of their Bondage there. But this he writes not according to his own Judgment, only ſets down the narration hereof out of one <hi>Artapanus</hi> an Heathen Author. Now we have no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to give Credit to his Relation in this particular; for albeit
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:62134:21"/>the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were oppreſſed with ſore Bondage, and had Cruel Task-maſters ſet over them, who urged them to the making of Brick in abundance: Yet the Scripture expreſly tells us to what uſe theſe Bricks were employed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.11. They did ſet Task-maſters over them, and they built the City <hi>Pithom</hi> and <hi>Raaemſes</hi> for the Treaſures of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> Thus they made them weary of their Lives by ſore Labour in Clay and in Brick, and in all Work in the Field, with all manner of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, which they laid upon them moſt cruelly, as v. 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Herodotus</hi> makes relation of one <hi>Menon</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Egypt</hi> who built <hi>Memphis,</hi> and therein <hi>Templum Vulcani</hi> a Temple to <hi>Vulcan</hi> great and memorable. And this I confeſs was moſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and long before the days of <hi>Moſes,</hi> if it be true which there is reported to him from the Prieſts of <hi>Egypt;</hi> namely, how they rehearſed to him out of a Book, the names of three hundred and thirty Kings, beginning from this <hi>Menon,</hi> and ending with <hi>Mevis</hi> the Father of <hi>Seſoſtris,</hi> who is ſuppoſed to be <hi>Shiſhak</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> mentioned in Scripture, who came to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with a great Army and took it, and carried away all the golden Shields that King <hi>Solomon</hi> had made. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God being very remarkable herein, as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended unto us 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.5, 6, 7, 8, Now <hi>Shiſhak's</hi> Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulation of <hi>Judea,</hi> came to paſs in the fifth year of <hi>Rehoboam</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> the year of the World 3029. by <hi>Lydiat,</hi> and 3033 in <hi>Uſher.</hi> Yet this <hi>Shiſhak</hi> was the Succeſſor of <hi>Mevis,</hi> the laſt of thoſe three hundred and thirty Kings in <hi>Egypt,</hi> whoſe names were related to <hi>Herodotus</hi> by the Prieſts of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And this <hi>Menon</hi> King of <hi>Egypt</hi> in <hi>Herodotus,</hi> is made all one with <hi>Amoſis</hi> by <hi>Lydiat.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euſeb. Prep. Evangel. <hi>l. 10. c. 9.</hi>
                  </note> I do not here mention how <hi>Porphyry</hi> makes <hi>Moſes</hi> more ancient than <hi>Inachus,</hi> who is more ancient then this <hi>Amoſis;</hi> nor how <hi>Africanus</hi> placeth him as Coaetaneous to <hi>Ogyges.</hi> Nor how <hi>Appion</hi> the Grammarian makes him of the ſame time with <hi>Amoſis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid.</hi> c. 10.</note> as in whoſe days he led the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Though in truth the Paſtoral Nation, which <hi>Manetho</hi> that Egyptian Hiſtorian mentioneth to have gone out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and planred themſelves in the Neighbour-Country of <hi>Syria</hi> about <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> were rather the Philiſtines, who came of the Caſlucheans and Caphtoreans, who were of the Egyptian Nation, and ſeized upon <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> and Maritime Coaſt of <hi>Judea;</hi> whoſe Trade alſo was the keeping of Sheep.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:62134:22"/>And to theſe refers that of <hi>Herodotus</hi> in the beginning of his Hiſtory, namely, that the <hi>Phoenicians</hi> came from the Red-Sea, by <hi>Phoenicians</hi> underſtanding <hi>Strians</hi> dwelling by the Sea Coaſt from <hi>Caſſiolis</hi> the border of <hi>Egypt.</hi> But theſe things are more clearly and truly ſhewn by <hi>Uſher</hi> in his Annals from <hi>A.M.</hi> 2114. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi> And how this was done in the days of <hi>Abraham,</hi> many hundred years before <hi>Moſes.</hi> But if any Man ſhall hence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that therefore Temples were in <hi>Egypt</hi> many hundred years before <hi>Moſes,</hi> by the Teſtimony of <hi>Herodotus.</hi> I anſwer, That <hi>Herodotus</hi>'s Teſtimony proceeded upon the Faith of the Egyptian Prieſts and their Regiſters, which deſerve no Credit with us Chriſtians; they making the King <hi>Menon</hi> to be many years more ancient than the World. Yet <hi>Lydiat</hi> ſhews how to ſalve their Credit in a tolerable way; namely, by ſuppoſing that the firſt reigning in <hi>Egypt</hi> (which he takes to have been ſixty years after the Diſperſion of the Gentiles, which is a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſixty one years after <hi>Noah</hi>'s Flood) by the Computation made by <hi>George</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine Manaſſes</hi> (out of the Fragments of ancient Hiſtorians, and ſet down in their Chronicles) all were not governed under one King; but look how many Cities ſo many Kings; like as <hi>Joſhua</hi> found it in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> when he entred among them with the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> And the Years of the Reigns of each King might be reckoned as ſucceeding one another, whereas indeed they reigned together in ſeveral Dynaſties at the ſame time. As that which followeth in the Relation of thoſe Prieſts made to <hi>Herodotus;</hi> namely, That in that vaſt ſpace of time the Sun changed his Courſe four times; as having twice riſen where now he ſets, and twice ſet where now he riſes; to aſtoniſh their Hearers with legends of great Admiration. They had an addition alſo, which was, That, before all theſe Kings, their Gods reigned, converſing familiarly with Men, and the laſt of them was <hi>Orus</hi> the Son of <hi>Oſiris.</hi> The ſame <hi>Herodotus</hi> writes, That the Egyptians much differed from the Grecians in the Eſtimation of their Gods: For whereas among the Grecians, the laſt of their Gods were <hi>Hercules,</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> and <hi>Pan:</hi> Contrariwiſe, among the Egyptians <hi>Pan</hi> was <hi>Vetuſtiſſimus,</hi> the moſt Ancient, even of the number of the firſt Rank, which were but eight; (and <hi>Latona</hi> was another of them, as elſewhere he tells us) <hi>Hercules</hi> was one of the ſecond Rank, which were twelve in number;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:62134:22"/>and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of the third Rank, which contained ſuch as were begotten of the former twelve: This <hi>Dionyſius</hi> is <hi>Oſiris,</hi> as he ſaith, whoſe Son <hi>Orus</hi> was the laſt of the Deities regnant among the Egyptians.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Of this <hi>Oſiris, Diodorus Siculus</hi> writes, which is alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his <hi>Preparat Evangel.</hi> l. 2. c. 1. That <hi>babuit Jovi Junonique parentibus ſacram aedem, item Diis caeteris aurea Templa,</hi> which carry a very ill Accent, that to <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Juno</hi> his Parents, he ſhould dedicate a Holy Houſe only, and to other Gods golden Temples. And withal he adds, That what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever was indeed verified of <hi>Oſiris</hi> the Egyptian, that <hi>Orpheus</hi> the Poet transferred unto <hi>Bacchus</hi> for the Honour of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians; even to that <hi>Bacchus</hi> whom <hi>Jupiter</hi> begat of <hi>Semele Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> his Daughter; as if <hi>Oſiris</hi> were no ancienter than ſo; but that <hi>Cadmus</hi> might have been his Grandfather. Whereas we have very good Ground and Teſtimony, concerning the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of <hi>Cadmus,</hi> as a Man unknown to the Grecians, till he left <hi>Phoenicia,</hi> which was at the time that <hi>Joſhua</hi> entered the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> with his great Hoſt of Iſraclites. And I do not think the Gods of the Egyptians were a making in thoſe days. He was a great and a proud King that oppreſſed <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and we know what Miſchief befel him and his People. <hi>Manetho</hi> makes mention of one <hi>Amenophis</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> whoſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes were, to be devoured of a Sea-Horſe: Probably this was that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> who was drowned in the Red-Sea. Great Benefactors while they lived, were honoured by Heathens with Divine Honour after their Death; but this <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was a Plague to the whole Land and People, and nothing likely that any of his Poſterity came to be deified by the Egyptians; and a long time after great Confuſion ſeized upon that Nation, witneſs <hi>Danaus</hi> flying out of <hi>Egypt</hi> into <hi>Thebes</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> from the Fury of his Brother <hi>Aegyptus;</hi> and after that <hi>Egyptus</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf leaving <hi>Egypt,</hi> and coming into <hi>Patre</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> mourning for the loſs of his Children. And we read in Scripture of the Gods of <hi>Egypt</hi> while <hi>Iſrael</hi> lived under them, yea, and how they were corrupted by them. <hi>Oſiris</hi> was a great <hi>Euergetes,</hi> or Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor, chiefly for the Invention of Tilling of the Ground, and Planting of Grapes, that of <hi>Virgil Georgic.</hi> 1.—<hi>Uncique puer monſtrator aratri;</hi> touching the firſt Inventer of the Plow. It was well, ſaith <hi>Servius,</hi> that he mentioned not his name, but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:62134:23"/>in general ſaith, The Boy that found it out. For it was not one Body that acquainted all the World with the Plow, but divers Perſons in divers Places. And if you ask who is chiefly meant here: His anſwer is, That ſome ſay <hi>Triptolemus,</hi> others <hi>Oſiris,</hi> Which is the truer of the two in the Judgment of <hi>Servius.</hi> So <hi>Sabinus Pliny</hi> relates, That <hi>Bizeſer</hi> the Athenian ſome that <hi>Triptolemus</hi> did this: But the Tradition is, That <hi>Oſiris</hi> was the firſt of all Mortals who Plowed with Oxen, in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial whereof, two Oxen are honoured of the Egyptians, <hi>Apis</hi> in the City <hi>Memphis,</hi> and <hi>Meuris</hi> in <hi>Heliopolis;</hi> and in the Offices of <hi>Iſis</hi> Ears of Corn are carried before, and in the time of Harveſt Ears of Corn are conſecrated unto her. Now <hi>Iſis</hi> was the Siſter of <hi>Oſiris,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pomponius,</hi> though that by the way is but a Figment, and <hi>Probus</hi> confirms the ſame. Nevertheleſs ſome have ſeemed to ſmell a Myſtery in this. And <hi>Coelius Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diginus,</hi> lib. 5. c. 12. obſerves, That before the Temples of the Egyptians was wont to be placed the Figure of <hi>Sphinx,</hi> to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie thereby, that the Wiſdom of their Theology was obſcure, and veſted in Fables; and that in the City <hi>Sais</hi> there is a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Palles</hi> (which ſome think to be <hi>Pallas</hi>) that hath this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription in the Face of it, <hi>I am that which was, and is, and ſhall be; my Veil no Mortal Man hath ever unfolded.</hi> Yet I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive theſe to be but Illuſions of Satan, to blanch and ſet a fair Face upon foul things, under the Pretence of Myſterious Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications. <hi>Coelius</hi> adds the Opinion of ſome to have been, That by <hi>Oſiris</hi> is meant no other thing than the River <hi>Nilus,</hi> the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing whereof, and the Mud which it brings ſoiling it, is a great means for the enriching of that Land. The ſame Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation is made by <hi>Euſebius, Preparat. Evangel.</hi> l. 3. c. 10. p. 115. And <hi>Suidas</hi> on the word <hi>Serapis</hi> writes, <hi>Hunc Deum alii Jovem eſſe dixerunt, alii Nilum propter modium quod in capite habet, &amp; cubilum, menſuram aquae ſcilicet, alii verò Joſeph.</hi> And in <hi>Forſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> there is a fair Derivation of <hi>Oſiris</hi> from the Hebrew <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>bos ille;</hi> for under ſuch a ſhape he was worſhipped; and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is in Hebrew the uſual name of the River <hi>Nilus,</hi> by reaſon of the blackneſs of the Mud which it brings with it. Others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Oſiris</hi> and <hi>Iſis</hi> to ſignifie the Sun and Moon; and firſt, theſe natural things being glorious to behold, were adored and invoked by them, according to that in <hi>Virgil,</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:62134:23"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Vos clariſſima mundi</l>
                  <l>Lumina labencem Coelo quae dueit is annum</l>
                  <l>Liber &amp; alma Ceres, veſtro ſi munere tellus</l>
                  <l>Chaoniam pingui glandem mutavit ariſta</l>
                  <l>Poculaque invent is Acheloia miſcuit uvis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Here <hi>Liber</hi> and <hi>alma Ceres</hi> are no other than the Sun and Moon; and <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Ceres</hi> are all one, <hi>Euſeb. Preparat. Evangel. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 1. and the ſame things are attributed to them in their kind by the<note n="*" place="margin">Martia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis ad So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Te Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapim Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phis vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur Oſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim.</note> Poet, which are uſually attributed to <hi>Oſiris</hi> and <hi>Iſis</hi> in their kind by Hiſtorians. Namely, the Proſpering and Maturating of Corn and Wine, according to their ſeveral pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Seaſons, wherein they are to be Sown or Planted, and the Fruit thereof to be expected. But leave we the Myſterious Signification, and come to the Hiſtorical Truth. <hi>Lydiat</hi> thinks that <hi>Menon</hi> the firſt King reigning over all <hi>Egypt,</hi> by what va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of names ſoever called (wherein there is found very great Variety as he ſhews) was the Man that married <hi>Iſis,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly received to be <hi>Oſiris,</hi> or <hi>Serapis;</hi> for theſe two are both one. But others conjecture, that <hi>Serapis</hi> being repreſented bearing a Buſhel upon his Head, doth fairly ſignifie <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who was ſo great a Benefactor to the whole Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and to King <hi>Pharaoh</hi> himſelf; and that eſpecially in providing Corn for them againſt the ſeven ſore years of Famine; and that by a wiſe managing of the abundance of the ſeven plentiful years. And this hath peculiar reference to that very particular which made <hi>Oſiris</hi> ſo renowned, namely, the Proviſion of Corn; and he was married to <hi>Aſenath,</hi> which taking away the laſt Syllable, founds very near to <hi>Iſin;</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Potipherah</hi> Prieſt of <hi>On,</hi> and the laſt two Syllables of his name comes near to <hi>Phorom</hi> the Argive, whoſe Siſter as ſome ſay, or Daughter as others ſay ſhe was; and that from <hi>Pharoneus</hi> the Argive, the Kings of <hi>Egypt</hi> took the name of <hi>Pharaoh, Lydiat</hi> conjectures, <hi>Schindler</hi> ſaith it ſignifies <hi>immunem eſſe,</hi> to be free from Taxes and Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, which is the Prerogative of Abſolute Kings; and it may ſeem to ſome, that in the ſeven plentiful years, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> took up the fifth part of all their Increaſe throughout the Land, by vertue of his abſolute Regal Prerogative. I am not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the manner of the Government of <hi>Egypt</hi> in thoſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:62134:24"/>days: But that the fifth part was rather bought by the King, to his ſingular great Advantage (as appeared by the event) Corn being little worth in thoſe plentiful years; I have this reaſon out of the Holy Text. For we read, that when the years of Dearth came, the Egyptians were at length driven to ſell their Land, after they had ſold their Caſtle, and all means ſailed them: And <hi>Joſeph</hi> bought all their Land for the King pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding them Corn for their preſent Neceſſity, both for Food and Sowing their Land; and the Bargain was this, They ſhould have the uſe of the Land ſtill, only the fifth part of their Increaſe they ſhould pay unto the King. Now if he had but a fifth part of the Harveſt after the Land was his, and he gave them the uſe of it; How unlikely is it, that by vertue of his Royal Prerogative, he either could or did take the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion when the Land was none of his, but theirs, for in this caſe it had been but a very ill Purchaſe, if hereby he had no more than he had formerly right unto, when as yet he had paid nothing for it. And this is the more unlikely, conſidering what courſe was taken to make the Purchaſe good; and that no Man might plead Right of Inheritance thereunto; for he changed their Habitations, ſo that albeit they might have as much Land as they had before; yet they had not each one the ſame Land which he enjoyed before.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Serapis</hi> had upon his Head <hi>diſcum,</hi> as the Latin renders it: But <hi>Alexander ah Alexandro,</hi> l. 4. c. 12. of his <hi>Genial days, Aegyptii Serapidi modium apponunt ſupra caput.</hi> The Egyptians repreſent <hi>Serapis</hi> with a Buſhel upon his Head, but like enough both took it from <hi>Suidas,</hi> and it is mentioned by <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> upon <hi>Auſt. de Civit. Dei,</hi> l. 18. c. 5. and the truth is in <hi>Coquaeus</hi> upon <hi>Auſtin de Civit. Dei,</hi> l. 18. c. 5. writes the ſame in theſe words, <hi>Nonnulli Serapin eſſe volunt Joſeph con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecratum, immani Sepulchro &amp; fano exornatum, in quo bos nutrieba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur in agriculturae Symbolum, quod famem ſeptennem ſingulari pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ab Aegyptiis detuliſſet.</hi> And this might be a very congruous Memorial of <hi>Oſiris,</hi> of whom it is written by divers, that <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus mortalium boves aratro junxit;</hi> the firſt who taught the World to Plow with Oxen: And for this cauſe the Oxe <hi>Apis,</hi> might be a fit Emblem of him, and of all ſuch who ever ſince have provided the People with Bread. Like as <hi>Menenius Agrippa</hi> (if my Memory fail me not) was the Man who for the like
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:62134:24"/>Service was honoured by the Romans, with making Coins in his name, and the Inſcription of an Oxe upon one ſide of it: And in this reſpect (as Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> obſerves) might the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clites think to repreſent God in the form of a young Bullock in the Wilderneſs, to notifie thereby, that God who provided Manna for them in the Wilderneſs. And it is like enough, that if the Egyptians had an <hi>Apis</hi> in thoſe days, ſome Oxe or other which they worſhipped, they by the Egyptians might be acquainted with the meaning of it, as a Memorial of <hi>Oſiris</hi> who taught them to Plow their Ground with Oxen, that ſo with greater eaſe they might have Corn yearly in abundance. Yet I deny not but <hi>Joſeph</hi> deſerved to be in everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance with them for this very cauſe. But the Text ſaith, A new King aroſe that knew not <hi>Joſeph;</hi> and though all <hi>Iſrael</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved well at the Egyptians hands for <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s ſake; yet we know how proudly they dealt with them, and how barbarouſly they carried themſelves toward them, not only oppreſſing them with Burthens, but cauſing their Male children to be caſt into the River <hi>Nilus,</hi> even <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s, who was a greater Bleſſing to them, and to their King eſpecially, than ever the River <hi>Nilus</hi> was; and the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> might have been ſo ſtill, had they uſed them well; for ten Perſons ſuch as <hi>Lot</hi> had ſaved <hi>Sodom;</hi> how much more 600000. And truly <hi>Pineda</hi> upon <hi>Job</hi> is of Opinion, that this <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was that <hi>Buſiris</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> of whoſe Barbarouſneſs in Sacrificing Strangers that came into his Country, the World ſo much talkt of. Surely had they made a God of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> they would not have plaid the Devils; yea, ſuch arrant Devils with his Poſterity. But the Lord, to make them amends in a congruous way, firſt turned the Water of <hi>Nilus</hi> into Blood, a fair means to revive the remembrance of their Mercileſs Courſe in Drowning the Hebrew Children; but when that would not ſerve the turn to bring them to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, the Lord drowned <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt in the Red-Sea: So periſh all thine Enemies, O Lord, but Grace, and Peace, and plenteous Redemption ever be upon the true <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Yet I rather think <hi>Oſiris</hi> to have been more ancient than <hi>Joſeph;</hi> Sure I am they had their Gods in the days of <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 6.26.</note> by whom the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were corrupted; and Hebrew Shepherds were an Abomination to the Egyptians,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 46.34.</note> not only in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:62134:25"/>the days of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but in the days of <hi>Joſeph.</hi> And <hi>Herodotus.</hi> writes, <hi>Non eoſdem Deos ſimiliter colunt univerſi Aegyptii praeter Iſidem &amp; Oſiridem quem Bacchum eſſe aiunt, Hos peraeque univerſi colunt.</hi> Herein they all agreed in worſhipping <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſiris</hi> not ſo in the worſhipping of other Gods. So that I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to tread in Mr. <hi>Lydiat</hi>'s ſteps, that the firſt King of <hi>Egypt Menon,</hi> or <hi>Ammon,</hi> or <hi>Amoſis,</hi> or <hi>Amuris,</hi> or <hi>Amenophis,</hi> to have been the Egyptians <hi>Oſiris,</hi> whoſe Memorial was an Oxe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was <hi>primus omnium mortalium qui boves aratro junxerat,</hi> the firſt that taught Men to Plow with Oxen; and thence might his name be derived, namely from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>bos,</hi> as <hi>Forſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> conceives; and <hi>Serapis,</hi> which at firſt was <hi>Sorapis,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <hi>Apis;</hi> for as <hi>Suidas</hi> ſaith, <hi>Sepulchrum bujus Apidis in quo est ejus corpus conditum, Alexandriam tranſlatum eſt;</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by Corruption it came to be called <hi>Sarapis,</hi> and laſt of all <hi>Serapis;</hi> and that <hi>Iſis</hi> his Queen was <hi>Io Argiva,</hi> the Story of whom the Poet calls <hi>Argumentum ingens in Virgil,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with drawn to the Life, he feigns <hi>Turnus</hi> his Buckler was flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, when he came into the Field againſt <hi>AEneas;</hi> and that becauſe he was the Progeny of <hi>Acriſius</hi> and <hi>Inachus</hi> Kings of <hi>Argos;</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>At laevem clypeum ſublatis cornibus Io</l>
                     <l>Auro inſignibat, jam ſet is obſita, jam Bos,</l>
                     <l>Argumentum ingens, &amp; cuſtos Virginis Argos</l>
                     <l>Caelataque amnem fundens Pater Inachus urna.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>For whereas Poets feign, that <hi>Io</hi> was turned into an Oxe by <hi>Jupiter</hi> being found by <hi>Juno,</hi> the truth ſeems to be no other than this; <hi>Oſiris</hi> was that <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and being repreſented by <hi>Bos mas;</hi> no marvel if hereupon ſhe becoming his Wife, they feigned her to be turned into <hi>Bos foemina.</hi> And whereas it is further feigned, that <hi>Argos</hi> was ſet by <hi>Juno</hi> to watch her; this <hi>Argos</hi> fairly repreſents <hi>Oſiris</hi> alſo her Husband, under another Notion, namely, as in an Hieroglyphical Interpretation he is taken for the Sun. For ſuch was the Oxe repreſenting <hi>Oſiris</hi> full of white Spots, and whoſe Hair was towards the Head; to ſignifie the Sun's proper Motion from Weſt to Eaſt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the general Motion of the Heavens from Eaſt to Weſt, (though Aſtronomers think otherwiſe in theſe days.) And the Stars of Heaven, by <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Doctrine, receive their Light
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:62134:25"/>from the Sun. Afterwards Poets feign that by <hi>Juno</hi>'s means ſhe was <hi>Oeſtro percita,</hi> plagued with an Hornet, and driven to fly into <hi>Egypt;</hi> the Truth whereof was no other than <hi>Oſtris</hi> his marrying of her, and carrying her over with him into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and there, ſaith <hi>Servius,</hi> ſhe was turned into <hi>Iſis:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de Civit. Dei, l. 18. c. 3. Jo filia I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachi.</note> this is that <hi>Argumentum ingens Virgil</hi> ſpeaks of, in reference to the true Story obſcurely carried, and dreſt by the Wits of Poets. But ſome rubs I find lying in the way, to hinder us in the Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſo great Antiquity of <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſiris.</hi> For whereas <hi>Dana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> that fled from his Brother <hi>Egyptus</hi> out of <hi>Egypt</hi> unto <hi>Argos</hi> in <hi>Grece,</hi> is ſtiled by Mr. <hi>Lydiat, à Belo Egyptio oriundus,</hi> by this <hi>Belus</hi> meaning <hi>Oſiris;</hi> as from whom <hi>Danaus</hi> was derived, but afar off, as who is accompted but the 10th King of <hi>Argos,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning from <hi>Inachus: Egyptus</hi> the Brother of <hi>Danaus</hi> I find ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Beli filius</hi> the Son of <hi>Belus,</hi> in a Monument of him erected, in a Temple of <hi>Serapis</hi> the City of <hi>Patrae,</hi> or <hi>Aroe</hi> a City of <hi>Achaia,</hi> as <hi>Pauſanias</hi> relates in his <hi>Achaicis.</hi> Yet this is not of force to take me off from following Mr. <hi>Lydiate</hi> in this. I underſtand <hi>filius</hi> here in a larger ſenſe than to take it for a Son begotten of <hi>Belus,</hi> and that it is no more than <hi>à Belo oriundus,</hi> one that was derived from <hi>Belus.</hi> For it is not credible that <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whom the Lord drowned in the <hi>Red-Sea,</hi> or any of his Poſterity, or his Father was <hi>Oſiris</hi> the great God of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> as before hath been argued. As alſo that the Gods of <hi>Egypt</hi> in <hi>Moſes</hi> his days, were not the ſame with the Gods of <hi>Egypt</hi> in the days of <hi>Joſeph.</hi> Another rub is caſt in the way by <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Auſtin, de Civit, Dei. lib. 18. c. 3. Pauſanias</hi> affirmeth, (ſaith he) that ſhe was the Daughter of <hi>Jaſius</hi> the ſixth King of <hi>Argos.</hi> Yet he confeſſeth, that <hi>Valerius Flaccus</hi> in his <hi>Argonautes, lib.</hi> 4. calls <hi>Jovem Inachidem;</hi> but withal he takes notice that he calls her <hi>Jaſtam virginem;</hi> as much as to ſay, the Daughter of <hi>Jeſius;</hi> yet ſhe might be called <hi>Inachides</hi> nevertheleſs, becauſe ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from <hi>Inachus,</hi> who was the firſt Founder of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Author of their Nobility. He gives alſo another Reaſon drawn from the Teſtimony of <hi>Euſebius</hi> both in his Chronicles, and in his tenth Book of Evangelical Preparation, teſtifying, that this <hi>Jo</hi> lived in the days of <hi>Triapas</hi> the ſeventh King of <hi>Argos,</hi> 400 years after <hi>Inachus.</hi> And indeed thus I find it in <hi>Pauſanias</hi> in his Corinthiacks, 58. that <hi>Triapas</hi> had two Sons, <hi>Jaſus</hi> and <hi>Agenow;</hi> and that <hi>Jo</hi> was the Daughter of <hi>Jaſus,</hi> and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:62134:26"/>ſo two Ages after <hi>Triapas,</hi> and but one before <hi>Danaus,</hi> who was after the time of <hi>Moſes</hi> his leading the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which I willingly confeſs is nothing probable; and though this be to my greater advantage in this preſent Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet I chooſe rather to hold with Mr. <hi>Lydiate</hi> ſtill; ſo utterly improbable and unlikely it is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Pharoah,</hi> who was drowned in the <hi>Red-Sea,</hi> or his Father, either was <hi>Oſiris,</hi> the times of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of <hi>Joſeph</hi> are ſo congenerous as touching the ſame Saperſtitions in courſe among the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> And as touching <hi>Panſanias</hi> this I find; that howſoever he writes thus in his Corinthiacks, yet in his firſt Book called <hi>Attica,</hi> reckoning up the Statues which were found in the Town of the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> two were of Women, <hi>Jo</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Inachus,</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſto</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Lycaon;</hi> whoſe Fortunes, he ſaith, were repreſented to be much the ſame, both as touching <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Love and <hi>Juno</hi>'s Wrath, and the Metamorphoſis of each, the one into a Cow, the other into a Bear. But then you will ſay, the more antient <hi>Oſiris</hi> was, the more evident it is that Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were in uſe long before <hi>Moſes,</hi> yea divers hundred years. Whereto I anſwer, though I grant the greateſt Antiquity aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to them, and do not help my ſelf with Teſtimonies out of the antient Fathers, as <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Stromat. Tertullian</hi> in his Apology, <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Juſtinus</hi> in his Oration againſt the Gentiles, and <hi>Tatianus</hi> in his Oration againſt the Greeks, and <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in his firſt Book againſt Hereſies, yea and of divers prophane Authors alledged by <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his tenth Book of Evangelical Preparation, and third Chapter, all teſtifying that <hi>Inachus</hi> King of <hi>Argos</hi> reigned in the days of <hi>Moſes:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Inachus,</hi> by the computation of times, was much elder, for which <hi>v. Uſher, A.M.</hi> 2174. Yet <hi>Diodorus</hi> his Teſtimony, of a Temple built by <hi>Oſiris</hi> himſelf, deſerves no credit; for he doth but relate what he heard from the Prieſts of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who told <hi>Herodotus,</hi> that between <hi>Orus</hi> his Reign, and that ancient <hi>Amoſis</hi> we ſpeak of, (Contemporary to <hi>Inachus</hi>) there were no leſs than 15000 years. And as for <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Juno,</hi> we know ſuch Deities received by the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> were no other than <hi>Oſiris</hi> and <hi>Iſis</hi> themſelves, which all the <hi>Egyptians</hi> worſhipt, as <hi>Herodotus</hi> teſtifies; ſo did they not any other God. And if there were any ſuch building of Temples in <hi>Egypt</hi> in thoſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times, when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were ſo much imployed in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:62134:26"/>of ſuch ſtore of Brick, in all likely hood theſe Bricks would have been imployed about ſuch ſacred uſes; but the Scripture teſtifies that they were imployed about the building of certain Cities, to be made Store houſes for the King. It is true, <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus</hi> was to ſeek whether <hi>Phoroneus</hi> or <hi>Merops</hi> was the firſt Founder of Temples: <hi>Phoroneus,</hi> we know, was the Son of <hi>Inachus,</hi> and ſecond King of <hi>Argos,</hi> and Brother to <hi>Jo</hi> or <hi>Iſis;</hi> but who <hi>Merops</hi> was, I have had much ado to find, from the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to divide, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a voice; of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> we read in <hi>Homer,</hi> as an attribute of Men, who alone of all bodily Creatures diſtinguiſh the Voice, into Words, Syllables, and ſingle Letters; whence it is called articulate, conſiſting as it were of ſeveral joints, as <hi>Coelius Rodiginus</hi> writeth; who by the way tells of a Cardinal (<hi>Aſcainus</hi> by name) who had a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rot which coſt him 100 Crowns, that could repeat the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed diſtinctly and accurately. I wonder of what Spirit he was, that took ſuch pains to teach a Parrot ſuch a leſſon: I preſume he was none of St. <hi>Francis</hi> his Auditors, a part of whoſe Legend it is, that he would preach the Goſpel even to bruit Creatures, ſo great was his deſire of the Salvation of all. The other Interpretation <hi>Rodiginus</hi> gives of the former Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy is in reference to the Diviſion of Languages, upon the Building of <hi>Babel</hi> for years after the Flood; and both of them are very ingenious in my judgment. But concerning any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whoſe proper name was <hi>Merops,</hi> I find nothing in <hi>Coelius,</hi> nor in divers others. But in <hi>Stephanus Bizantinus</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I find <hi>Merops</hi> himſelf, ſaid to be the Son of <hi>Triopas,</hi> and from him the People of <hi>Coos</hi> called <hi>Meropes,</hi> and that Iſland <hi>Meropis;</hi> and ſo, much about the time of <hi>Jo</hi> the ſecond, whom <hi>Euſebius</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to have lived in the days of <hi>Triopas,</hi> as <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> relates upon the 18th Book of <hi>Auſtin, de Civitate Dei,</hi> and the third Chapter. <hi>Antoninus Liberalis,</hi> in his Metamorphoſes, makes this <hi>Merops</hi> to be cooetaneous to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> for thus he writes, <hi>Num.</hi> 36. as it is tranſlated (for he is a Greek Author;) <hi>Jupiter poſtquam Titanibus pulſis, Saturno regnum ademit, Aegem (quae mammam ei praebuit) immortalitate donavit, &amp; ejus imago extat in aſtris: aureum autem canem Templi Cretenſis cuſtodiae, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecit. Hunc ſuffuratus Pandareus Meropis filius in Sipylum adduxit, Cuſtodiendum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> dedit Tantalo Jovis &amp; Plutus filio; cum autem ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quanto poſt tempore Pandareus in Sipylum veniſſet, canem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> repoſceret:
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:62134:27"/>Tantalus depoſitum ejuravit.</hi> So that the Son of <hi>Merops</hi> by this Author's accompt was but cooetaneous to <hi>Tantalus,</hi> who was the Father of <hi>Pelops,</hi> Grandfather to <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> chief of the <hi>Grecians</hi> at the <hi>Trojan</hi> War. Now touching <hi>Clemens Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> he was to ſeek whether it were <hi>Phoroneus</hi> or <hi>Merops,</hi> or ſome other, <hi>qui eis poſuerunt templa,</hi> who erected Temples. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like he had ſome evidence that made him incline to think, that <hi>Phoroneus</hi> was the firſt; other evidence that ſwayed him ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, and made him think <hi>Merops</hi> was the firſt; and third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he had ſome ground to conceive that neither of theſe but ſome other, after both theſe, was the firſt. Now of theſe Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences we can ſay nothing by way of examining them, becauſe we do not know them. <hi>Arnobius</hi> in his ſixth Book ſpecifies three by name, in queſtion about the primacy of building Temples, and they are <hi>Phoroneus</hi> not <hi>Argivus,</hi> (of whom I underſtand <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> to have delivered his mind in this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) but <hi>Phoroneus Egyptius;</hi> the other two mentioned by him are <hi>Merops,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus;</hi> and the third and laſt <hi>Aeacus,</hi> who as he is placed after the former two, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered according to their Age; ſo it ſeems he was later than both the former. And for the laſt of the three to be the firſt in this kind of Devotion, he alledgeth no meaner Author than <hi>Varro;</hi> who was commonly accounted the moſt learned of all the <hi>Latins.</hi> Now <hi>AEacus</hi> was but the Grandfather of <hi>Achilles,</hi> and ſo but two Generations before the Wars of <hi>Troy,</hi> which in common accompt, is not above 66 or 67 years; whereas <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> led the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt</hi> above 300 years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Wars of <hi>Troy.</hi> Therefore when <hi>Varro</hi> writes, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> reports him, <hi>de Civit. Dei, lib.</hi> 18. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. that the <hi>Sicyonians</hi> did ſacrifice at the Sepulchre of <hi>Thurimachus,</hi> the 7th King of the <hi>Sicyonians;</hi> ſurely at that time there was no Temple built at that Sepulchre, for ought <hi>Varro</hi> found in all his reading. And again, when <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, in the ſame place, that when <hi>Phegous</hi> the Brother of <hi>Phoroneus</hi> was dead, there was a Temple built at his Sepulchre, by reaſon (as he gueſſeth) that <hi>Phegous</hi> was a devout Prince, and had in his time erected Chappels for Divine Service, he had not this from <hi>Varro;</hi> nay <hi>Varro</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth no Temples until many years after. Not to mention that both <hi>Clemens</hi> and <hi>Arnobius</hi> thought it more likely that <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneus</hi> rather than his Brother was the firſt Erector of Temples,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:62134:27"/>yet neither of them had any ſure and certain grounds for their Opinions.</p>
               <p n="20">20. Thus much concerning the <hi>Graecians</hi> and <hi>Egyptians;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing remains to be added concerning the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> and <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> and the Original of Temples amongſt them alſo: <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus Siculus, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. writing of <hi>Semiramis</hi> and her building of <hi>Babylon,</hi> adds that, <hi>In vrbis medio templum Jovi erexit quem vocant Babylonii Belum;</hi> In the midſt of the City ſhe built a Temple to <hi>Jupiter,</hi> whom the <hi>Babylonians</hi> call <hi>Belus:</hi> But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al he ſaith that of this Temple, <hi>Nihil certi pronuntiari poteſt, cam &amp; Scriptores diſcordent, &amp; opus ipſum vetuſtate collapſum ſit;</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can certainly be affirmed, conſidering that Writers dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and the Work it ſelf is fallen to decay through Age. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodotus</hi> alſo makes mention of the Temple of <hi>Belus,</hi> but he makes no mention of him that built it; and as for <hi>Semiramis, Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus</hi> makes her to precede <hi>Nitocris</hi> but five Ages, which is ſhort of 200 years; for three Ages makes an 100 years by his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt. And <hi>Nitocris</hi> he writes to have been the Mother of <hi>Labynitus,</hi> againſt whom <hi>Cyrus</hi> waged War. No <hi>Cyrus</hi> we know took <hi>Babylon</hi> whilſt <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> reigned, who alſo was ſlain that night wherein <hi>Babylon</hi> was entred into by the <hi>Perſians,</hi> through the Channel of the River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> whoſe ſtream was turned another way by the Army of <hi>Cyrus;</hi> yet we confeſs the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Monarchy was far more ancient than this <hi>Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramis Herodotus</hi> writes of, (and that by Scripture evidence) having been founded by <hi>Nimrod,</hi> that mighty hunter before the Lord, whom ſome conceive to be <hi>Belus Babylonius;</hi> and I nothing doubt but the remembrance of ſo great a Man, and the firſt Monarch, might be preſerved by figures made of him, and theſe figures become Idols; like as in the days of <hi>Sem,</hi> yea, and <hi>Noah,</hi> alſo Idols were among the Poſterity of <hi>Sem,</hi> in the Family of <hi>Terah.</hi> The beginning of <hi>Nimrod</hi>'s Monarchy is placed by <hi>Lydiat</hi> and <hi>Uſher</hi> the 14th year after the Diſperſion of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple through the confuſion of Tongues, that is 115 years after the Flood, 185 before the Death of <hi>Noah,</hi> and 335 before the Death of <hi>Sem;</hi> which they ground on the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſearcht into by <hi>Calliſthenes</hi> the Philoſopher, and Follower of <hi>Alexander</hi> in his <hi>Perſian</hi> War: for he found by his Calculation of thoſe Antiquities, that the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Monarchy began 1903 years before <hi>Babylon</hi> was taken by <hi>Alexander.</hi> A little after
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:62134:28"/>the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Monarchy began, as Scripture teſtifies, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. for <hi>Moſes</hi> having mention'd the beginning of <hi>Nimrod</hi>'s Kingdom to have been <hi>Babel,</hi> and <hi>Erech,</hi> and <hi>Accad,</hi> and <hi>Calne</hi> in the Land of <hi>Shinar, vor.</hi> 10. he forthwith adds, that out of that Land (to wit the Land of <hi>Shinar</hi>) went <hi>Aſhur</hi> and built <hi>Nineveh,</hi> and the City <hi>Rehoboth,</hi> and <hi>Calab.</hi> This <hi>Aſhur</hi> was the Second Son of <hi>Sem, ver.</hi> 22. It is thought his Eldeſt Son was <hi>Ninus</hi> the Firſt, from whoſe Name was the Name <hi>Ninive</hi> given to the City built by him; and <hi>Ninive</hi> I find is all one with <hi>Ninus,</hi> in <hi>Herodotus,</hi> whoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom began 1360 years before <hi>Lycurgus</hi> gave Laws to the <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> according to the Computation of <hi>George</hi> the Monk, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd by <hi>Scaliger,</hi> with one years only difference, provided we underſtand <hi>Aſhur</hi> to have reigned 60 before his Son <hi>Ninus;</hi> and from the firſt of <hi>Ninus,</hi> to <hi>Lycurgus</hi> his giving Laws, are 1300 years. And which Act of <hi>Lycurgus</hi> was 97 years before the Account of <hi>Iphitus</hi> his <hi>Olympiads</hi> began. Now this was 1485 years before the Reign of the latter <hi>Belus Babylonius, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladan,</hi> or <hi>Nabonazar</hi> by Name, who in all likely hood was that <hi>Belus</hi> which <hi>Herodotus</hi> ſpeaks of, and <hi>Diodorus Siculus.</hi> For this <hi>Baladan,</hi> or <hi>Nabonazar,</hi> the ſecond Babylonian <hi>Belus,</hi> began his Reign but the twelfth year of <hi>Iotham</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> a little before the Foundation of the Walls of <hi>Rome</hi> was laid by <hi>Romulus.</hi> But whereas <hi>Scaliger</hi> conceives there were two Dinaſties in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonia,</hi> one ſucceeding the other 368 years before the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Belus,</hi> whom yet he accounts more ancient by 125 years than the Computation of <hi>Calyſthenes</hi> doth reach unto: This <hi>Lydiat</hi> conceives to have no colour of Truth. And thus I have diſpatched this Enquiry about the <hi>Antiquity of Temples,</hi> according to my Power, and preſent Leiſure.</p>
               <p>Yet I deny not, but that as Men, before there were any Temples, did worſhip their deceaſed Anceſtors, and offer Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices at their Sepulchres; as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teſtifies they did, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording unto <hi>Varro</hi> his Obſervations, <hi>de Civit. Dei, lib.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Apud ſepulchrum ſeptimi ſui Regis Thurimachi; ſacrificare Sicionois ſolere,</hi> The <hi>Scythians</hi> were wont to ſacrifice at the Sepulchre of their Seventh King. <hi>Thurimachus,</hi> which <hi>Thurimachus</hi> is ſaid to have reigned amongſt the <hi>Sicyonians</hi> before <hi>Inachus</hi> reigned amongſt the <hi>Argives;</hi> thô others make <hi>Inachus,</hi> the Firſt King of <hi>Argos,</hi> to be more ancient than <hi>AEgialcus.</hi> Firſt King of the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:62134:28"/>
                  <hi>Sicyonians,</hi> as <hi>Ludovious, Vives</hi> relates, upon the 18th. Book of <hi>Auſtin. de Civit. Dei, chap.</hi> 3. And <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> in his <hi>Corinthiacks, pag.</hi> 54. ſhews where was the Sepulchre of <hi>Phoroneus;</hi> and adds, <hi>Phoroneo quoque noſtra etiamnum aetate parentant,</hi> to this day they do offer Sacrifice to <hi>Phoroneus,</hi> to wit, at his Sepulchre: And no marvel if they were of their Opinion, who knew no other Gods, than the Ghoſts of Dead Men, from whom they received Anſwers, lying over their Graves, as <hi>Melo</hi> and others write of certain People of <hi>Afriea,</hi> call'd <hi>Augitae.</hi> Likewiſe, I deny not, but that in proceſs of time, the Sepulchres of great Men were fair Houſes or Structures, built to no other end, but that the Bodies of great Perſonages might lie therein, as it were in State. Such were the <hi>Mauſolaea Regum Sepulchra,</hi> faith <hi>Caelius Rodigimus, l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 10. the Sepulchres of Kings; the firſt of them, <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolaeum,</hi> having its Name from <hi>Mauſolus</hi> (as the ſame Author writeth, <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>c.</hi> 6.) King of <hi>Halicarnaſſus,</hi> as <hi>Pauſanias</hi> relates in his <hi>Arcadia;</hi> and he adds, that it was built <hi>ea operis magnitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, atque omni ornamentorum magnificentia, ut Romani rei mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo adducti, magnificentiſſima quaeque apud ſe monumenta, Mauſolea appellarint;</hi> So great, and ſo adorned, that the <hi>Romans</hi> admiring it, afterwards called all ſuch magnificent Monuments by the Name of <hi>Mauſolaea:</hi> And he writes ſtrange things of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher of one <hi>Helena</hi> an Hebrew Woman in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> before it was deſtroyed by <hi>Adrian.</hi> And <hi>Lilius Giraldus,</hi> in his Book <hi>de Vario Sepeliendi ritu,</hi> writes, that Temples and Churches had their Original from hence; his words are theſe, <hi>Fuit verò uſque adeò antiquis ſepulchrorum cura, ut non aliundè templorum &amp; ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum aedium originem deductam, diligentiſſimi ſcriptores tradant, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius &amp; Lactantius. Qua de re &amp; Clemens Alexandraeus in adbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione ad Graecos, ſi ita rectè <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> interpretamur ſic ſcriptum reliquit; Superſtitio (inquit) Templa condere perſuaſit quae enim prius hominum ſepulchra fuerunt, magnificentius condita Templorum appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latione vocata ſunt. Nam apud Lariſſaeam civitatem in arce in Templo Palladis Achriſii ſepulchrum fuit quod nune ſacrarii loco cale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratur. In arce queque Athenienſi ut eſt ab Anticcho in nono Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riarum ſcriptum, Cecropis, ſepulchrum fuit. In Templo verò Palladis jacet Erichthonius. Iſmarus autem Eumolpi atque Dairae filius in Eleuſine una cum Celei natabus ſepultus, &amp; reliqua, quae multa Clemens collegit &amp; ab eo Euſebius quae in Latinis codicthus non ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur.</hi> He adds, That as Temples, ſo Images and Idols (as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:62134:29"/>touching the publick uſe of them) took their Originals from Sepulchres alſo, and he alledgeth <hi>Diophantes</hi> the <hi>Làcedemonian,</hi> in his Books of <hi>Antiquities,</hi> for the Proof of this. But whether there were ſuch in <hi>Egypt</hi> in the days of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> or <hi>Moſes,</hi> I am very uncertain: Suppoſe they had their Bull <hi>Apis,</hi> ſevered and kept in a Placè by himſelf; this required only <hi>Septum,</hi> a Place compaſſed about with a Wall, where might be aſſo ſome Place of Succour, with a Covering to reſort unto in time of Rain, Hail, Storm, or Tempeſt; though we read not ſo much as this, of thoſe ancient Times. Only we read of thoſe Times, that ſome Creatures were accounted Sacred by the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and it was not lawful to kill ſuch; nay, it was Abomination to ſacrifice any ſuch. Or ſuppoſe they had Images of thoſe Gods whom they worſhipped, yet Temples were not neceſſary for this; for, as I have ſhewed before, many ſuch, together with Altars alſo, were erected <hi>ſub Divo,</hi> in the open Air. I will conclude all with that which <hi>Alexander ab Alexandro</hi> writes in his genial days, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Perſae nec Deorum imagines habent, nec Templa erigunt (crant enim aedium ſacrarum &amp; ſimulacrorum everſores) ſed in loco mundo &amp; excelſorum, praecatione Diis victimas immolant, quod à pleriſque uſitatum invenimus. Nam Carmeli Deus colebatur, cui nec Templum erat nec ſimulachrum, ſed ara tantum &amp; divinus cultus. Iudaei mente ſola, unum numen colunt, ideo nulla apud eos ſimulachra non modo Templis, ſed nec urbibus inſunt. Germani queque nullam humani oris ſpeciem Diis, prae eorum magnitudinè dederunt, nec Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pla dicarunt: ſed lucos &amp; nemora Deorum nominibus appellant; illa velut ſacra templa venerantur.</hi> And in his 2 <hi>d.</hi> Book, cap. 2. <hi>Nulla ficta apud Lycurgum vel picta imago fuit: quippe hominum aut ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malium ſpecies Diis tribui vetuit. Templum verò in quo colebatur deſuper patens foramen habuit, quia nefas duxerunt Terminum Deum pacis &amp; juſtitiae cuſtodem, ſub tecto conſpici. Sic Iovi, Soli, Lunae, &amp; Deifidio in aperto mundo, Templa hypaethra &amp; ſub divo veteres extruxere, quod à Graecis ſaepe factitatum novimus, ut his Diis hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paethra templa conſtituant, ſicut aedes Iovis Pulverii in Attica, ſemper ſine tecto erigebatur. Graeci verò Minervae in ſumma parte aedium ſine victima ſacrificant; AEſculapio in montibus. Apud Perſas nulla dicabantur templa diis, quia cum ſolem praecipuun numen, &amp; Deorum maximum colant, mundum univerſum illi Templum eſſe dixerunt. A Bithynis uſurpatum legimus, ut adoraturi montium cacumina conſcendant, &amp; ſine templis Iovem Pappam ſalutent, ſicut Scythae Pap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paeum.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:62134:29"/>Quae etiam Diogenis opinio fuit, qui mundum fanum Dei ſanctiſſimum exiſtimavit. Fucre autem Termini, atque Fidei Templa juxta aedem Iovis optimi maximi, in capitolio primum a Numa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructa, cui ſacrum feſt Terminalibus in agris, ſexto ab urbe mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liario, ſub patente caelo fieri ſolebat.</hi> With the Engliſhing of this I mean to ſet a period to this Diſcourſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Perſians</hi> have neither Images of Gods, nor do they erect Temples (rather their courſe was to pull down to the ground Holy Houſes and Images) but in a clean Place, in high Places, with Prayers they did ſacrifice to the Gods, which we find to have been in uſe with many. For at <hi>Carmel</hi> God was worſhipped, where was neither Temple nor Image, but an Altar only, and Divine Worſhip. The <hi>Iews</hi> in their minds only worſhip One God, and therefore with them are no Images, neither in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples nor in Cities. The <hi>Germans</hi> alſo give no ſhape of Man to the Gods, by reaſon of their Greatneſs, nor dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Temples to them; but Groves and Woods they call by the Names of Gods, and they reverence them as holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. <hi>Lycurgus</hi> ordained no painted or graven Image, as who forbad to expreſs the Gods in the ſhape of Men, or other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And as for the Temple wherein God was worſhipped, that was open at the top, as thinking it unlawful that the God <hi>Terminus,</hi> the Preſerver of Peace and Juſtice, ſhould be ſeen under a Roof or Covering. In like ſort, Men of ancient Times built Temples to <hi>Iupiter, Sol, Luna,</hi> and to <hi>Deus Fidius,</hi> in the open Air, which they called <hi>Hypoethra,</hi> as much as to ſay, under the cope of Heaven, open; which was the <hi>Graecians</hi> uſual courſe, as the Houſe of <hi>Iupiter Pulverius</hi> in <hi>Attica</hi> was always without a Roof. And the <hi>Graecians</hi> ſacriſiced to <hi>Minerva</hi> on the tops of their Houſes, without ſlaughter made of any Beaſt; and to <hi>AEſculapius</hi> upon the Hills. Amongſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> no Temples were conſecrated to the Gods; beeauſe being of Opinion that the <hi>Sun</hi> was the chief Power Divine, and the greateſt of Gods, they ſaid the whole World was his Temple. We read it to have been the <hi>Bithynians</hi> Practice, that when they worſhipped, they went to the tops of Hills, and there ſaluted <hi>Iupiter Pappas</hi> without any Temple, as the <hi>Scythians</hi> did <hi>Pappaeus.</hi> Such alſo was the Opinion of <hi>Diogenes,</hi> who maintained the World to be the moſt holy Temple. As for the Temples of the God <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus,</hi> and the God <hi>Fides,</hi> they were by the Houſe of <hi>Jupiter
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:62134:30"/>optimus Maximus,</hi> in the Capitol, which were firſt built by <hi>Numa Pompilius;</hi> to whom Holy (or religious) Office was performed on the Terminal Feaſts in the Field, and under the open Heaven, ſix miles diſtant from the City.</p>
               <p>I might add our Learned Antiquary <hi>Inego Iones</hi>'s Opinion, concerning that ſtrange Structure of <hi>Stoneheng</hi> on <hi>Salisbury-Plain,</hi> that it was originally no other than <hi>Templum ſub Divo,</hi> a Temple all open at the top, (ſuch as are mentioned by <hi>Alexander ab Alexandro;</hi>) but I reſer the curious to his Book, and conclude this firſt Diſſeratation.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books ſold by <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the Bible and Three Crowns near <hi>Mercers-Chappel.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Richard Baxter</hi>'s Narrative of the moſt memorable Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of his Life and Times. Faithfully publiſhed from his own Original Manuſcript, by <hi>Mat. Sylveſter.</hi> Folio.</p>
            <p>Sermons and Diſcourſes on ſeveral Divine Subjects. By the late Reverend and Learned <hi>David Clarkſon,</hi> B. D. ſometime Fellow of <hi>Clare-Hall, Cambridge:</hi> Recommended by the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Mr. <hi>Iohn Howe,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Mat. Mead.</hi> Fol.</p>
            <p>A Body of Practical Divinity, conſiſting of above 176 Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons on the Leſſer Catechiſm. Compoſed by the Reverend Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter:</hi> With a Supplement of ſome Sermons on ſeveral Texts of Scripture. By <hi>Tho. Watſon,</hi> ſometime Miniſter of St. <hi>Stephens Walbrook, London.</hi> Recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by 26 Miniſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Fol.</p>
            <p>Forty nine Sermons upon the whole Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Coloſſians.</hi> In Three Parts. By the Famous Miniſter of the Reformed Church in <hi>Paris,</hi> Mr. <hi>Iohn Daille,</hi> with two Epiſtles of Dr. <hi>Tho. Goodwin,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Iohn Owen.</hi> Fol.</p>
            <p>A Paraphraſe on the New Teſtament, with Notes, Doctrinal and Practical, fitted for the uſe of Religions Families, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By the late Reverend Mr. <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>Annotations upon the Holy Bible. In Two Volumes Folio. By Mr. <hi>Mat. Pool.</hi> Third Edition, with an Addition of a
<pb facs="tcp:62134:30"/>Concordance by Mr. <hi>Sam. Clark;</hi> and Contents to each Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Fierce Juſtification by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; written origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in Latin by <hi>John Fox,</hi> Author of the Book of Martyrs. Tranſlated into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>A Brief Concordance to the Holy Bible, in a new Method. By <hi>Sam. Clark,</hi> M.A. Twelves.</p>
            <p>The Confirming Work of Religion, or its great Things made plain by their Primary Evidences and Demonſtrations: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the meaneſt in the Church may ſoon be made able to render a ſolid and rational Account of their Faith. By <hi>Rob. Fleming.</hi> Publiſhed by <hi>Dan. Burgeſs.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>Husbandry ſpiritualiz'd; or, The heavenly Uſe of earthly Things. By <hi>Iohn Flavel,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel. Octavo.</p>
            <p>A Brief and Plain Expoſition and Paraphraſe of the whole Book of the Revelation, from Chapter to Chapter, and from Verſe to Verſe. By <hi>Sam. Cradock,</hi> B. D. ſometime Rector of <hi>North Cadbury</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>The Goſpel-Myſtery of Sanctification, open'd in ſundry Practical Directions, ſuited eſpecially to the Caſe of thoſe who labour under the Guilt and Power of Indwelling Sin. To which is added a Sermon of Juſtification. By Mr. <hi>Walter Marſhal,</hi> late Preacher of the Goſpel. Octavo.</p>
            <p>Spiritual Songs; or, Songs of Praiſe to Almighty God, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeveral Occaſions: Together with the Son of Songs, which is <hi>Solomon</hi>'s firſt turn'd, then paraphraſed in Engliſh Verſe. To which may be added Penetential Cries. The 4th Edition, with an Addition of <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus.</hi> By <hi>Iohn Maſon,</hi> M.A. 8 <hi>vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Good of Early Obedience; or, The Advantage of bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Yoke betimes. By <hi>Mat. Mead.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>A Preſent for the Sick that have been recover'd. By <hi>Nath. Vincent.</hi> Octavo.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Nath. Vincent</hi>'s Converſion of the Soul. Octavo.</p>
            <p>—His Touchſtone of Grace and Nature. Octavo.</p>
            <p>—Heaven or Hell upon Earth, or a Diſcourſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Octavo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Steel</hi>'s Diſcourſe of old Age, tending to the Inſtruction, Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Comfort of Aged Perſons. Octavo.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
